<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Emerai par emeras, Extraordinary dayes, or, Sermons on the most solemn Feasts and fasts throughout the year viz. Christmas-day, Ash-Wednesday, Good Friday, Easter-day, Ascention-day, Whit-Sunday : whereunto are added two other sermons / by John Torbuck ...</title>
            <author>Torbuck, John, d. 1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62955</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21672</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12297392</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12297392</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59072</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62955)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59072)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 927:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Emerai par emeras, Extraordinary dayes, or, Sermons on the most solemn Feasts and fasts throughout the year viz. Christmas-day, Ash-Wednesday, Good Friday, Easter-day, Ascention-day, Whit-Sunday : whereunto are added two other sermons / by John Torbuck ...</title>
                  <author>Torbuck, John, d. 1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 115 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L. Lichfield ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Greek at head of title.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [21]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term>Festival-day sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Extraordinary Dayes.</hi> OR SERMONS On the moſt Solemn FEASTS and FASTS throughout the Year. <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>CHRISTMAS-DAY.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>ASH-WEDNESDAY.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>GOOD-FRYDAY.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>EASTER-DAY.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>ASCENTION-DAY.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>WHIT-SUNDAY.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto are added two other Sermons.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN TORBUCK, M. A.</hi> Rector <hi>of</hi> Ludgerſhal <hi>in Wilt-ſhier.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 14.5, 6.</hi>
                  </bibl> One man eſteemeth (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) one day above another.</p>
               <p>He that regardeth a day, regardeth it to the Lord; and he that regardeth not the day to the Lord, he doth not regard it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>L. LICHFIELD,</hi> Printer to the Univerſity, 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:2"/>
            <head>To the worthily Hon<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. and Right Worſhipful, Colonel <hi>VVilliam Aſhburn-ham,</hi> One of his Majeſties prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Officers at Court, and Burgeſs for <hi>Ludgarſhal</hi> in the County of <hi>Wilts.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>All Happineſs,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Worthy</hi> SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce no man, be he never ſo great a ſtranger to your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, can be unacquainted with your Virtues &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo well known to your Country, and particularly
<pb facs="tcp:59072:3"/>your own Borough, (whoſe Inhabitants are ready at all times to throw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at your feet in thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acknowledgment of your many favours) among theſe, <hi>Sir,</hi> (now Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath made me one of of them) may this my Mite of gratuity be accepted of.</p>
            <p>I thought theſe Tracts not improper for ſuch a Patron, both in reſpect of their ſtyle and ſubject: The Style being poor, may yet, <hi>Sir,</hi> we know travel abroad
<pb facs="tcp:59072:3"/>with courage &amp; ſafety un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Your Protection. The Subject indeed High, our <hi>Solemn Feſtivals,</hi> were at the ſame time with you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to their due ſplendor. And I have this to ſay, the plainer theſe Compendious diſcourſes, the more ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their Auditory, being the ſubstance only of what was delivered to my own charge: Nor ought theſe Truths any more (then ſome our more ſolid Gentry now adayes) be the leſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed
<pb facs="tcp:59072:4"/>of, for their ordinary garbe. Wherein, what I have bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, I have choſen ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee too troubleſome, with Interlinings, then not honeſt, to repay again, in the exact quotation of the Authors: I would have no man for me ſuch a <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras,</hi> as in pett to turn Atheist, finding me not thunder-ſtruck for wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully fathering anothers labour. To Conclude, <hi>Sir,</hi> If theſe my Honeſt, (though weak endeavours) prove
<pb facs="tcp:59072:4"/>any way profitable, with your pardon, and good lik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; I have my wiſh, whoſe cheifeſt ambition is to beg leave, to ſubſcribe,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Yours in all cheerfully devoted ſervice, <hi>JOHN TORB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CK.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Preface</hi> To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He</hi> Great Diespiter, <hi>(as the Poet calls him) that</hi> Father <hi>of</hi> dayes: <hi>God, who made every day,</hi> Gen. 1. <hi>hath made ſome dayes twice, that (as well as in reſpect of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> fiat, <hi>ſo of a ſpecial</hi> facia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; <hi>of a common Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſo of ſome ſignal and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar mercy) we may ſay of
<pb facs="tcp:59072:6"/>them with the Pſalmist's Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis,</hi> 18 Pſal. 24. Theſe be the dayes which the Lord hath made, we will be glad, and rejoyce in them. <hi>And as there is a time of</hi> joy, <hi>ſo a time to</hi> weep, 3. Eccleſ. 4. <hi>as a time of</hi> mirth, <hi>ſo a time to</hi> mourn. <hi>The Lustre of Gods more glorious favours is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, by rendring the light of the</hi> Moon <hi>as the light of the</hi> Sun, <hi>and the light of the</hi> Sun, <hi>ſevenfold, as the light of ſeven dayes. Now what ſenſeleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and unworthineſs muſt it needs be, to take no notice of thoſe</hi> times <hi>which God hath ſo ſplendedly marked out for
<pb facs="tcp:59072:6"/>us, with the paſſages of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct love? Such are the Feſtivals of Chriſts</hi> Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Reſurrection, Aſſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c. <hi>And as Gods ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar bounty hath advanced ſome dayes to a</hi> ſuperlative bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>ſo our</hi> notorious ſins, <hi>have brought others, to a</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal cloudineſs. <hi>The former, make up our</hi> Set-Feaſts, <hi>deſign'd for publick</hi> praiſe <hi>and</hi> joy: <hi>Theſe latter,</hi> Set-Faſts, <hi>for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn</hi> ſorrow <hi>and</hi> penance. <hi>But there are a peeviſh gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, (who loving to tread</hi> Antipodes <hi>to the Churches cuſtome) are pleaſed with nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; against whom, we may
<pb facs="tcp:59072:7"/>justly take up our Saviours complaint,</hi> 11. Mat. 17. We have piped unto you, and ye have not danced, we mourned to you and ye have not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If theſe may Object;</hi> praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>God for a Saviour, and</hi> Repentance <hi>for ſins, are du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties required</hi> every day, <hi>and therefore what needs all this adoe? Beſides, can we (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſay they) depoſe, thoſe</hi> ſet-times, <hi>we ſo much ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to be the</hi> very <hi>times of</hi> Chriſts birth, Paſſion, Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, &amp;c. <hi>Doth not Saint</hi> Paul <hi>too ſeverely check</hi> time-obſervers, 4 Gal 11. <hi>with an,</hi> I am afraid of you?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What is</hi> alwaies <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, muſt be needs pure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs to ſlight then, when the Church hath commanded it, only becauſe</hi> She hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>What is</hi> alwaies <hi>requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, may it not be</hi> ſometimes <hi>requiſite, in a more</hi> ſolemn <hi>manner? They may with the ſame Argument, condemn the</hi> duties <hi>of the</hi> Sabboth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Apoſtle in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned place to the</hi> Galati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>ſpeaks only againſt the</hi> Superſtitious <hi>obſervation of</hi> Judaical Feſtivals.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:8"/>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Are</hi> theſe <hi>the</hi> very <hi>times of Chriſts Birth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Here they think they have us upon advantage, without remedy: But give me leave to ſay (ſuch is the different accompt of time, and upon many reſpects ſo undiſcernable the loſs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) that I ſhould think him ſomwhat hardy, ſhould prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to ſwear, to the</hi> Preciſe <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs of</hi> any <hi>day we keep. It is enough to any ſober man, that the Church hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them for ſuch, or ſuch</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities, <hi>esteeming them the very times, (as near as ſhe could be informed by the beſt tradition) nor can it be any
<pb facs="tcp:59072:8"/>other than ill nature, conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and obſtinacy, to cavil with her herein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I like them the worſe becauſe theſe</hi> Time-Levellers <hi>have been commonly found to aime at the levelling of Kings, and Kingdoms as well as</hi> Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies, <hi>to their diſcontented and factious humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall I tell thee Chriſtian, devoutly obſerve what the Church hath appointed in all her reaſonable commands (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them at leaſt, to be the very dayes, for what they were enjoynect) this will be a maine help to raiſe thy medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, to an Ecstatical height
<pb facs="tcp:59072:9"/>and an abundance of freſh ſupplyes of comfort will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue to thee hereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Title is,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Extraordinary Daies, <hi>or</hi> Daies above Daies, <hi>becauſe Theſe in our Church Service-Book have the Precedency of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in their proper Pſalms, (the marrow of Devotion) proper</hi> Communion Prefaces, <hi>most</hi> Articles of our Creed, <hi>are contained in them, and theſe be the moſt most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in that moſt pious and potent Supplication the</hi> Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>where we paſſionately call for mercy by thoſe Acts done on them, ſaying, By the Myſtery of
<pb facs="tcp:59072:9"/>thy</hi> Holy Incarnation, <hi>by thy</hi> Holy Nativity and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, <hi>by thy Baptiſm, Fast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Temptation, By thy Agonie, and bloudy ſweat, by thy</hi> Croſs and Paſsion, <hi>by thy Precious Death and Burial, by thy Glorious</hi> Reſurrection and Aſſenſion, <hi>and by the</hi> Comming of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Good Lord deliver us!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reader, <hi>This Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath not a little affected me (I proffer thee no worſe) and by Gods bleſſing, may have the ſame effect on thee, which is the earneſt Prayer, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Faithful, (though, unworthy) Servant <hi>J. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Titles of the</hi> Sermons, <hi>with their</hi> Texts, <hi>contained in the Book.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt Sermon On Chriſtmas-day. Or the Nativity of Chriſt.
<q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1</hi> Luke <hi>16.</hi>
                     </bibl> And they came with haſte, ad found Mary and Joſeph, and the Babe lying in a Manger.</q>
               </item>
               <item>Second Sermon, On Aſh-wedneſday, Or the Prevalency of Prayer, and Faſting.
<q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>17.</hi> Mat. <hi>21.</hi>
                     </bibl> Howbeit this kind goeth not out, but by Prayer, and Faſting.</q>
               </item>
               <item>Third Sermon, On Good-Fryday, Or the Paſſion of our Saviour.
<q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>26</hi> Mat. <hi>39.</hi>
                     </bibl> O my Father if it be poſſible let this Cup paſs from me: nevertheleſs not as I will, but as thou wilt.</q>
               </item>
               <item>Fourth Sermon, On Eaſter-day, Or the Reſurrection.
<q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>24</hi> Luke <hi>34.</hi>
                     </bibl> The Lord is riſen indeed.</q>
               </item>
               <item>Fift Sermon, On Holy-Thurſday, Or the Aſcenſion.
<q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>4</hi> Epheſ. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </bibl> He that deſcended, is the ſame alſo that aſcended up, far above all Heavens, that he might fill all things.</q>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59072:11"/>
               <item>Sixth Sermon, On Whit-Sunday, Or the Ineſtimable Gift of the Holy Ghoſt.
<q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>8</hi> Acts <hi>20.</hi>
                     </bibl> But Peter ſaid unto him, Thy money periſh with thee, becauſe thou haſt thought that the gift of God may be purchaſed with money.</q>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Moſes Mis-us'd, Or the Magiſtrate's Authority moſt Impiouſly, and Impudently affronted.</head>
               <item>Preached at the Summer Aſſizes at <hi>Abingdon</hi> 1669.
<q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>7</hi> Acts <hi>27.</hi>
                     </bibl> But he that did his neighbour wrong, thruſt him away ſaying, who made thee a Ruler and a Judge over us?</q>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lex Innata.</hi> Religion Born with us.
<q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Rom. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </bibl> Theſe thaving not the law, are a law unto themſelves.</q>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:11"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 37. l. 9. r. <hi>Gaius.</hi> p. 38. l. 25. r. <hi>prayers.</hi> p. 73. l. 18. r. <hi>bones.</hi> p. 86. l. 14. r. <hi>four.</hi> p. 87. l. 18. r. <hi>Humane.</hi> l. 27. r. <hi>contact.</hi> p. 103. l. 16. r. <hi>came.</hi> l. 22. r. <hi>Apoſtoli.</hi> p. 106. l. 20. r. <hi>of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> 7. Serm. p. 12. l. 26. r. <hi>doers.</hi> p. 19. l. 11. r. <hi>ſleep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe, and what other Faults (through the Authors abſence from the Preſs) have eſcaped, Curteous</hi> Reader <hi>Correct.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59072:12"/>
            <head>FIRST SERMON ON <hi>Chriſtmas-Day,</hi> OR <hi>The Nativity of Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. Luke 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And they came with haſt, and found Mary and Joſeph, and the Babe lying in a Manger.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are <hi>two pieces of Wood</hi> that become the <hi>Jews</hi> chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>ſtumbling-block,</hi> and the Pagans ſcorn, and yet are the main <hi>props</hi> in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians <hi>Creed,</hi> and <hi>ſupporters</hi> in his <hi>Comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:59072:13"/>
            <p>I mean the <hi>Cratch</hi> &amp; the <hi>Croſs,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. c. 23. the <hi>one</hi> unavoidably accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying Chriſts <hi>birth,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> his <hi>death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what the bleſſed Jeſus (when he came to viſit us in great humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity) was not <hi>aſhamed</hi> to <hi>undergo</hi> for us, we have infinite leſs reaſon to be <hi>aſhamed</hi> to <hi>own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God forbid, But that we ſhould <hi>glory</hi> (with St. <hi>Paul</hi>) as in the <hi>Croſs</hi> of Chriſt, (6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 14.) ſo in his <hi>Cratch</hi> too, the one is in order to the other, (Myſterie of Divinity) the <hi>everliving God</hi> was born <hi>here,</hi> to be capable to <hi>ſuffer</hi> there; and <hi>both</hi> for our <hi>ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence, the <hi>Manger</hi> and the <hi>tree</hi> (ſeem they never ſo deſpicable) are greater Monuments of Gods love to Mankind, than the glorious <hi>fabrick</hi> of the <hi>Univerſe,</hi> for who will deny our <hi>Redemption</hi> to be a mercy excelling the <hi>Creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then is a great <hi>Feaſt,</hi> as the day of our Redeemers <hi>Birth,</hi> ſo of his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> too, and that only at the Sign of the <hi>Manger,</hi> Hoc erit ſignum, <hi>this ſhall be it,</hi> ſaith the Angel, <hi>v.</hi> 12. To this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59072:13"/>let us make haſt with thoſe in the Text, <hi>And they came with haſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe words divide themſelves into 4 Parts. 1 <hi>Inventores.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Text in</hi> 4 <hi>parts.</hi>
               </note> 2 The <hi>Perſonae In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventae.</hi> 3 The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi</hi> 4 The <hi>Quomodo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Inventores</hi> or <hi>Perſons finding.</hi> They came. 2 The <hi>Perſonae Inventae,</hi> or <hi>Perſons found,</hi> Mary, and Joſeph, and the Babe. 3 The Ubi or <hi>place</hi> where they were found, <hi>In a Manger.</hi> 4 The <hi>Quomodo, how</hi> they found them, or what means they uſed here. <hi>They came with haſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Perſons finding, <hi>They came,</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons finding Shepheards.</note> this refers to the <hi>Shepheards,</hi> v. 8. abid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>field,</hi> keeping watch over their ſlocks by <hi>night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if any are offended at <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Theoph. <hi>Excubantes, quaſi extra cubare dicas, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adeò ſub dio pernoctare</hi> Beza) and ſay the <hi>Shepheards</hi> being at this time <hi>abroad</hi> without doors, muſt needs turn our <hi>December</hi> Chriſtmas <hi>out of doors</hi> quite (ſuppoſing it improbable, that they would in ſo <hi>cold</hi> a part of the year, take up their lodging in the <hi>open field</hi>) they muſt conſider the <hi>diverſities</hi> of <hi>Climates,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:59072:14"/>and the <hi>vigilancy</hi> of <hi>Countrey-men,</hi> when neceſſity requireth.</p>
            <p>The great confluence of all ſorts of people and ſtrangers at this general <hi>tax, v.</hi> 1. might make them look about them with the more care and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quare vetuſta traditio Eccleſiae non temerè nobis rejicienda eſt.</hi> Caſaubon.</p>
            <p>The Shepheards did properly ſeek for and find, (as Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) the <hi>(b) Chief, (c) Great,</hi> and the <hi>(d) Good</hi> Shepheard <hi>(e)</hi> of our <hi>ſouls;</hi> This bleſſed <hi>Lamb of God</hi> (now newly yeaned) <hi>that taketh away (f) the ſins of the world.</hi> (b) 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. c. v. 4. (c) 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 20. (d) 10. <hi>Joh.</hi> 11. (e) 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. (f) 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 29.</p>
            <p>God ſaith of his begotten, <hi>Let all the Angels worſhip him,</hi> 1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. which honour as he confers on thoſe <hi>glorious Spirits,</hi> ſo in his infinite mercy, he is pleaſed to allow <hi>men</hi> likewiſe, (whoſe nature he took, 2. <hi>Heb.</hi> v. 16. and not the others) and amongſt theſe, the moſt <hi>ordinary</hi> plain Countrey-men <hi>Shepheards.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59072:14"/>
            <p>Chriſt coming to undertake for us in the <hi>meaneſt</hi> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ition that might be,
<note place="margin">What may be lear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed a from the Shepheards.</note> hath every thing <hi>ſuitable</hi> thereto, a <hi>homely place</hi> for his birth, and <hi>homely gueſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor will I part with my Shepheards, till from them I learn, that as there is requiſite a due diſtance between Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, and Inferiours, ſo this ought to be free from all manner of <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Contempt,</hi> ſince God accepteth of the <hi>loweſt</hi> as well as the <hi>higheſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we know (bleſſed Jeſus) that thou art <hi>(h) he,</hi> that ſhould come, not do we look for <hi>another,</hi> ſince accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the undeniable Character of the true Meſſiah (which thou thy ſelf haſt given) <hi>the</hi> (i) <hi>poor here have the Goſpel Preached unto them.</hi> The <hi>Shepheards</hi> this day receive the <hi>(k) Evangelium,</hi> the firſt <hi>glad tidings</hi> of a Saviours birth; <hi>vobis natus eſt,</hi> v. 10. (h) 11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. (i) <hi>v.</hi> 5. (k) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. v. 9.</p>
            <p>To conclude; the <hi>Joy</hi> of this <hi>Birth</hi> is (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>to all people,</hi> v. 10. Chriſt deſcended, as from <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> and a liſt of <hi>Kings,</hi> ſo from <hi>Booz,</hi> and <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> plain <hi>Countreymen:</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59072:15"/>Now, he came <hi>for</hi> them, <hi>from</hi> whom he came; which Intimates that all ſorts and conditions of men from the <hi>Scepter</hi> to the <hi>Sheep-crook,</hi> are intereſſed in a Saviour.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Shepheards</hi> firſt hear and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare a Saviour, perhaps that the <hi>plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the men might add the greater credit to their relation. <hi>Abfuit ab iſs fingendi voluntas, &amp; aſtutia, quia rudes fuêre.</hi> Lactantius.</p>
            <p>I paſs now from the <hi>Inventores,</hi> or <hi>perſons finding,</hi> the Shepheards, <hi>(they came and found)</hi> to the perſonae inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae,
<note place="margin">The perſonae Inventae. Mary, and Joſeph, and the Babe. Why Mary named be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Joſeph.</note> 
               <hi>perſons found,</hi> viz. <hi>Mary,</hi> and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> and the <hi>Babe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe be the <hi>Parents</hi> and the <hi>Child;</hi> but why <hi>Mary</hi> before <hi>Joſeph?</hi> the <hi>Wife</hi> before the <hi>Husband?</hi> This doth not quit the <hi>woman</hi> of her duty of <hi>ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> 5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 22, 23, 24. and wring the ſtaff of <hi>Preheminence, Rule,</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> out of the <hi>mans</hi> hand, to put it into <hi>hers.</hi> But perhaps <hi>ſhe</hi> was found firſt (though not far <hi>one</hi> from the <hi>other;</hi>) or rather it ſeems to me, as if the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Holy Ghoſt would imply hereby, that <hi>Mary</hi> of the two, hath
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59072:15"/>the greateſt <hi>ſhare</hi> in this Birth. <hi>Mary</hi> is the <hi>real</hi> Mother, <hi>Joſeph</hi> but the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted</hi> Father of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>That <hi>He was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, born of the Virgin Mary,</hi> is an <hi>Article</hi> of our <hi>faith,</hi> without any talk of <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence ſinful, vile, polluted <hi>Adam</hi>'s off-ſpring, <hi>Man,</hi> touch not this <hi>Holy Maid:</hi> and hence all baſe and unchaſt thoughts; that which is conceived in her, is of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which <hi>Conception</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sicut ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis calefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente ſole,</hi> &amp;c. Aug. de temp. Ser. 181.</note> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> makes more plain unto us by the ſimilitude of a <hi>Worm,</hi> which Chriſt compares himſelf to, 22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. <hi>I am a worm,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and no man;</hi> i. e. not <hi>conceived</hi> after the <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>men;</hi> but as the <hi>worm</hi> by the heat of the Sun onely, is formed of <hi>mud</hi> or <hi>ſlime:</hi> ſo Chriſt was conceived of our <hi>fleſh,</hi> by the ſecret <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> and <hi>operation</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> alone.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec poteſt doceri niſi à donaate, nec poteſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſei, niſi à ſuſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>piente. St.</hi> Bern. on the Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Melchiſedec without Father,</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus thus <hi>miraculouſly conceived; Mary</hi> yet acts the part of a <hi>Mother</hi> in bearing and <hi>bringing forth</hi> this her <hi>firſt born,</hi> 5, 6, 7. verſes.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59072:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>From hence forth all generations ſhall call thee bleſſed,</hi> 1. Luk. 48.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou art the King of glory O Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou art the Everlaſting Son of the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet, <hi>when thou tookeſt upon thee to deliver man, thou didſt not abhor the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quantus eſt qui na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt, Sed quantus eſt qui de</hi> Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine <hi>natus eſt?</hi> Aug. Hom. 32. <hi>pag.</hi> 340.</note> Virgins Womb.</p>
            <p>Mary! in this, <hi>He that is mighty hath magnified</hi> thee. 1. Luk. 49. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Goſpel ſhall be Preached, there ſhall alſo</hi> this <hi>be told.</hi> 26. Mat. 13.</p>
            <p>Thy name ſtands regiſtred in that Breif, <hi>(our belief)</hi> which muſt have paſſage over all the world, and we will never remember thee, but with <hi>love</hi> and <hi>reverence</hi> next to adoration.</p>
            <p>(If I might not be thought too ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious and impertinent) I could tell here, how that this <hi>name,</hi> once named, (out of aweful reſpect to the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin</hi>) did once <hi>ſtop</hi> a young Gallants <hi>luſt;</hi> in its full deſign, and work a notable <hi>Reformation</hi> in him. The <hi>Story,</hi> we may read at large in <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taigne</hi>'s Eſſayes, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 46.</p>
            <p>But as the poor ſimple man, muſt needs <hi>Saint. Pontius Pilate,</hi> becauſe his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59072:16"/>name was ſuffered in the Creed, will I (on the contrary) altogether <hi>deſpiſe Joſeph,</hi> for being left out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſeph</hi> then,
<note place="margin">Joſephs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription.</note> (though of mean <hi>occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation</hi>) a <hi>Carpenter.</hi> 13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 55. yet is of <hi>Royal deſcent:</hi> of the houſe and linage of <hi>David,</hi> v. 4.</p>
            <p>As to his <hi>Civil condition,</hi> he is <hi>noble</hi> (belonging to the <hi>tribe</hi> of <hi>Judah</hi>) and therefore repairs to their <hi>Metropolis Bethlehem,</hi> to be <hi>taxed,</hi> v. 4, 5.</p>
            <p>As to his <hi>vertuous diſpoſition,</hi> he is a <hi>juſt man, and obedient to the Divine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</hi> 1. Mat. 19.24.</p>
            <p>I would fain leave them, as they were found, <hi>together.</hi> A loving <hi>pair,</hi> and ſo not far <hi>one from the other.</hi> Indulgent <hi>Parents,</hi> and ſo <hi>both near the Babe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Methinks I ſee the over joy'd <hi>Mother</hi> ſmiling upon her heavenly <hi>Off-ſpring:</hi> whil'ſt <hi>Joſeph</hi> admires his <hi>Virgin Wife, ſhe</hi> buſily wrapping and ſwadling his beauteous body; whil'ſt <hi>he</hi> as cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully waiteth and tendeth on this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Nurſe.</p>
            <p>'Tis Honour over and above ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to <hi>Joſeph</hi> only to be <hi>husband</hi> to <hi>her,</hi> whoſe child he durſt not own to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59072:17"/>have begotten, <hi>For the Holy Ghoſt came upon her, and the power of the higheſt did overſhadow her: wherefore that Holy thing which was born of her, is called the Son of God.</hi> 1. Luke 35.</p>
            <p>Which brings me to the <hi>Babe,</hi> to whom I long indeed to come as the ſubject matter of this Feſtival.</p>
            <p>As Contemptibly as here he ſeems to lye,
<note place="margin">The Babe who he is.</note> this is none other than a <hi>Saviour, Chriſt the Lord,</hi> v. 11.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">A Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</note> A Saviour, <hi>&amp; ſoter hoc quantum eſt?</hi> ſaith <hi>Tully.</hi> How great are the thoughts of a <hi>Saviour?</hi> if but for the <hi>Body?</hi> But this is a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Saviour, this <hi>Babe</hi>'s name is <hi>Jeſus,</hi> becauſe, <hi>he ſaves</hi> his people from their <hi>ſins,</hi> 1. Mat. 21. Neither is <hi>this ſalvation</hi> in <hi>any other.</hi> 4. Acts 12.</p>
            <p>A Saviour,
<note n="1" place="margin">Chriſt.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſtus dicitur à Chryſmate</hi> i.e. <hi>unctione</hi> St. Auſtin de temp. Ser. 181.</note> Anointed, for of a truth this <hi>Holy Child Jeſus</hi> was Gods <hi>ſpecial anointed,</hi> 4. Acts 27. with the <hi>oyle of gladneſs above his fellows,</hi> 45. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. i. e. as the
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hall<hi>'s Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphr. on the Text.</hi>
               </note> King, Prieſt, and Prophet of his Church: God hath endued his aſſumed humanity with all divine graces above all meer man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59072:17"/>
            <p>Chriſt comes fully <hi>qualified,</hi> for the work of a <hi>Mediator,</hi> or <hi>compleat</hi> Saviour, purpoſely deſigned hereto, with his <hi>Commiſſion Patent</hi> from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; <hi>for him hath God the Father ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> 6. Jo. 27.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt the <hi>Lord.</hi>
               <note n="3" place="margin">The Lord.</note> There be <hi>Gods many,</hi> and <hi>Lords many,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. ch. 5. But Holy Babe, Thou only art <hi>the Lord.</hi> There be many <hi>Chriſti Domini,</hi> the Lords <hi>Chriſts</hi> or anointed, yet but one <hi>Chriſtus Dominus,</hi> the <hi>Lord Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is the Lord, <hi>Lord of Lords, and King of Kings.</hi> 17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. The Lord <hi>coeternal</hi> and <hi>coequal</hi> with <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> begotten of him before all worlds, <hi>God of God, very God of very God,</hi> ſaith the Nicene Creed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such a Lord,</hi> that the very Pagan
<note n="†" place="margin">Auguſtus.</note> Emperour, 'tis reported by <hi>Grotius, lib.</hi> 7. c. 2. upon the ſame day that this <hi>Babe</hi> was born, forbid any by Edict to call <hi>him Lord,</hi> That all Lordſhip might be aſcribed to him. To whom he in great devotion erected an Altar with this inſcription, <hi>Haec eſt ara primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniti dei.</hi> Suet.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59072:18"/>
            <p>The <hi>Delphick</hi> Oracle is ſaid to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the <hi>Deity</hi> of this <hi>Babe,</hi> vid. <hi>Balduin. de Caſ. Conſc.</hi> pag. 75. One of the <hi>Sybils</hi> to prophecy concerning it: <hi>Plato</hi> to believe it: But whate're be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> Stories; <hi>Scripture</hi> doth ſufficiently prove him our <hi>Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel, God with us.</hi> 1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. In this word (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> Ser. Nat. 9. pag. 75.) is implyed both natures, <hi>El</hi> ſignifies Gods <hi>cum plenitudine pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis, God</hi> in his full <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> God with all that ever he can do. So is Chriſt, ſaith <hi>Athan.</hi> in his Creed, <hi>perfect God;</hi> Immanu <hi>with us:</hi> one of us, <hi>perfect man</hi> too; and that in the <hi>Infancy</hi> of our nature, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Babe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Babe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt a Babe.</note> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>dicitur pro</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Euſt.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) implyes a child newly born hanging at his Nurſes breaſt.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed <hi>Babe!</hi> Well may thy name be called <hi>Wonderful,</hi> 9. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 6. what
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſti Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitas ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentio cola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Baſ. Hom. in Sanctam Chriſti Nat.</hi> p. 246.</note> a myſterious Birth is this? where <hi>Incomprehenſibility</hi> is <hi>cradled,</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">1. Rev. 8.</note> Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity hath a <hi>beginning,</hi> the Rock of ages not a <hi>day old,</hi> Almightineſs made <hi>weak,</hi> the Word, 1. <hi>Jo.</hi> 1. <hi>not able to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59072:18"/>ſpeak a word,</hi> Immenſity (l) <hi>whom the Heaven of Heavens cannot contain,</hi> but a <hi>ſpan long,</hi> 2. Lam. 20. He (m) <hi>that hath gathered the winds in his fiſts, and bound the waters in a garment, who hath eſtabliſhed all the ends of the Earth,</hi> is <hi>himſelf</hi> in a Virgins <hi>arms,</hi> in <hi>clouts,</hi> in a <hi>ſtable.</hi> The great (n) creatour and (o) preſerver of all things, is content to become a <hi>Creature,</hi> to <hi>take Being</hi> from <hi>her</hi> to <hi>whom</hi> he <hi>gave Being:</hi> and <hi>nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> from her, to whom he gives <hi>ſuſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Bleſſed is the womb that bare thee, and the Paps which thou haſt ſucked.</hi> (l) 1. <hi>K.</hi> 8. <hi>ch.</hi> 27. (m) 30. <hi>Pro.</hi> 4. (n) 1 <hi>Col.</hi> 16. (o) <hi>v.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>Oh whether hath thy love for us tranſported thee, infinitely below thy ſelf in <hi>Humiliation,</hi> which muſt needs tranſport us beyond our ſelves in <hi>admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Ubi, <hi>or place Chriſt was found. The Manger. Why ſo?</hi>
               </note> This <hi>Humility</hi> doth further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate it ſelf in the <hi>ubi,</hi> or place Chriſt was found in, the <hi>Manger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ſo?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Take the <hi>Holy Ghoſts</hi> reaſon, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>there was no room in the Inn.</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">No Room in the Inn.</note> In reſpect of the meanneſs of her Husband <hi>Joſeph,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59072:19"/>and that the concourſe of people was ſo great: ſo Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> in his Paraphraſe on the Text. O ignorance and ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude! <hi>no room</hi> for him on <hi>Earth,</hi> who prepares us ſuch glorious <hi>manſions</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> 14. <hi>Jo.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">This was the Angels Sign to find Chriſt.</note> This was the <hi>ſign</hi> given of the Angel, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. without this, the Shepheards might have ſought Chriſt long enough, and not have found him: Let them alone, ſay nothing to them (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> in his Ser. of the Nat. 12. <hi>p.</hi> 110.) when they came to <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> they would never go to an <hi>Inn</hi> or <hi>Oſtrie,</hi> but the very <hi>beſt houſe</hi> in the Town, or if to an Inn, to the <hi>faireſt Chamber</hi> in it, or to a <hi>Chamber</hi> at leaſt.</p>
            <p>They would have expected a <hi>chief perſon</hi> in a <hi>chief place,</hi> a Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, ſomewhat Lord and Saviour like, in a <hi>Crimſon Mantle,</hi> in an <hi>Ivory-Cradle,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But this is his ſtate of <hi>Humiliation,</hi> and as he is
<note n="†" place="margin">Athan. <hi>in his Creed.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Inferiour to God, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his</hi> Manhood, ſo inferiour to <hi>man</hi> touching his Manger. <hi>Being made like unto the Beaſts that periſh,</hi> 49. Pſal. 20.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59072:19"/>lower then this he could not well go.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">This Sign runs Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to mans ſinning.</note> Our Saviours <hi>Signs</hi> runs counter to mans <hi>ſinning,</hi> and ſo it muſt: No fruit will ſerve us but the <hi>reſerved tree;</hi> no preferment but a <hi>Dii eritis,</hi> 3. <hi>Gen.</hi> no <hi>Tower</hi> but one that ſhall <hi>reach to Heaven,</hi> 11. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. Now contrary to all this, is Chriſt's <hi>low, common,</hi> and <hi>deſpiſed</hi> Manger.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Pride</hi> be the direct way to <hi>Hell,</hi> quite back agen <hi>Humility,</hi> muſt be the way to Heaven.</p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note n="4" place="margin">This Sign was proper to Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards.</note> This <hi>Sign</hi> was proper to <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards,</hi> to give them encouragement for their admiſſion to Chriſt, this ſhall be a Sign <hi>unto you,</hi> v. 12. There will be no <hi>Porter</hi> to <hi>ſtop</hi> the <hi>paſſage,</hi> no <hi>ſtrict Guard</hi> to <hi>hinder</hi> your <hi>acceſs</hi> to the Manger.</p>
            <p n="5">5.
<note n="5" place="margin">A Sign that Chriſt ſtood not in need of any external pomp.</note> This is a <hi>Sign</hi> that Chriſt ſtood not in need of any <hi>external Signs</hi> or <hi>means</hi> to ſet him forth: But was, and is (of himſelf) <hi>independently</hi> glorious.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Indifferent</hi> perſonages commonly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet after the <hi>gaudieſt</hi> dreſs; a <hi>Pearl</hi> of great price retains its value, as well in a <hi>Manger,</hi> as in the <hi>Coſtlieſt Cabinet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59072:20"/>
            <p>The more <hi>unexpected</hi> is his greatneſs (by the baſeneſs of his Sign) the more it is to be <hi>admired.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6.
<note n="6" place="margin">The lower the ſign, the higher his love.</note> The <hi>lower</hi> the <hi>Sign,</hi> the <hi>higher</hi> Chriſts <hi>love</hi> to be ſo far abaſed for us.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The <hi>viler</hi> the <hi>Sign,</hi> the viler <hi>ſin,</hi> that brought him to it,
<note n="7" place="margin">The viler the ſign, the viler ſia.</note> the <hi>uncleanneſs</hi> of our <hi>hearts</hi> brought Chriſt to ſuch an <hi>unclean</hi> and <hi>noyſome</hi> Birth-place.</p>
            <p n="8">8.
<note n="8" place="margin">This ſign was to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the the Jews.</note> This <hi>Sign</hi> might be a <hi>Sign</hi> that God had a mind (in his infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Juſtice) to <hi>puniſh</hi> the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy and ingratitude of the <hi>Jews,</hi> mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>Manger,</hi> the <hi>Sign</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> rather <hi>Signum Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum,</hi> than <hi>Creditum:</hi> rather <hi>ſpoken againſt,</hi> 2. <hi>Luk.</hi> 34. than <hi>believed:</hi> That their haughty ſpirits were ready to cry out with as great ſcorn as they 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10 <hi>c.</hi> 27. <hi>How can this man ſave us?</hi> They fancied that the Meſſias ſhould have a <hi>Princely Court</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and never dream't of a <hi>Manger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9.
<note n="9" place="margin">This was a ſign Chriſt intended no greatneſs at his firſt coming.</note> This <hi>Sign</hi> was a <hi>Sign,</hi> Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended no greatneſs, no <hi>temporal great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> at his <hi>firſt</hi> coming. His <hi>beginning</hi> was a <hi>Cratch,</hi> his <hi>end</hi> no other <hi>(exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus)</hi> or <hi>lifting up,</hi> (8. <hi>Jo.</hi> 28.12. <hi>Jo.</hi> 32.)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59072:20"/>then the Croſs. The <hi>one</hi> was propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to the other, ſome deſcribe a <hi>Cratch</hi> (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> in his Ser. of the Nat. 12. <hi>pag.</hi> 3.) to be made <hi>Croſs wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>What</hi> God hath <hi>ordained,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Laſtly, This ſign God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained,</hi> &amp;c.</note> (for this Manger, was not left out of the Holy Pages of his eternal, wiſe <hi>decrees,</hi> 40. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 28.) <hi>what</hi> Chriſt gladly <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted</hi> of, 40. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. <hi>what</hi> the Holy Ghoſt in Scripture teſtifies, the <hi>Angels</hi> openly <hi>Preached</hi> and <hi>Sung</hi> to, 11, 12, 13. <hi>verſe,</hi> we have no cauſe at all to be offended at, but with all love, joy, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and aſtoniſhment to adore this <hi>Babe lying in a Manger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note n="4" place="margin">Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo, <hi>or how Chriſt was found.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Its ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note> I come to the <hi>Quomodo</hi> how Chriſt was found; or what means the <hi>Shepheards</hi> uſed here, and that was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>They came with haſt,</hi> this ſignifies.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. An
<note n="(r)" place="margin">4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>(from whence comes <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) and</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Endeavour
<note n="(s)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>studium,</hi> 2. Cor. 8. ch. 16.</note> Study</hi> and earneſt <hi>care</hi> for Chriſt. The <hi>deſire of all Nations</hi> (2. Haggai 8.) is worthy of all this; <hi>Religion</hi> doth not indulge <hi>lazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59072:21"/>Heaven will not <hi>drop</hi> in our mouths, and we ſit ſtill; the promiſe is made to the willing and obedient, 1. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 19.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. An <hi>urgent</hi> and <hi>forcible</hi> Haſtning. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The <hi>Angels haſtned Lot,</hi> 19. Gen. 11. or Hurried him by violence, for <hi>ver.</hi> 12. 'tis ſaid, they <hi>laid hold</hi> on him, and brought him forth, whilſt he lingred, which implyes that the Kingdom of Heaven ſuffereth <hi>violence,</hi> and the <hi>violent</hi> take it by force, 11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>There is a natural <hi>lingring</hi> in our purſuit of Heaven. The <hi>way</hi> is either too <hi>far,</hi> the <hi>night</hi> (of perſecution) is too <hi>dark,</hi> or our <hi>flocks</hi> the World, too <hi>dear</hi> to be left; but we muſt with the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, with a full <hi>reſolution</hi> and ſacred <hi>force</hi> break through all <hi>theſe,</hi> if we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to come to Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> A preſent, ſpeedy, and ſwift <hi>Acceleration (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>viam contrahere</hi>) a <hi>Contraction</hi> of the way by taking up of our feet nimbly.</p>
            <p>This implyes a <hi>redeeming</hi> of the (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) the <hi>Inſtant opportunity</hi> to come to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59072:21"/>Chriſt. <hi>To day,</hi> whil'ſt it is <hi>to day,</hi> 3. Heb. 7.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Delayes are dangerous;</hi> if you <hi>ge</hi> not <hi>now</hi> the <hi>babe</hi> may be <hi>gon,</hi> and the <hi>ſign</hi> to find him in <hi>vain.</hi> If we uſe not <hi>timely</hi> means, they may in Judgement be taken from us, or prove ineffectual to us.</p>
            <p>Behold <hi>now</hi> is the <hi>accepted time, now</hi> is the <hi>day</hi> of <hi>ſalvation,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. c. 2. The Angel begins this dayes news with an <hi>Ecce,</hi> a <hi>Behold</hi> tidings of great Joy, A Saviour Chriſt the Lord, whoſe Birth this day ſpeaks <hi>Peace</hi> on <hi>Earth; Good will</hi> towards <hi>men,</hi> for which we muſt render <hi>Glory to God on high.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>Application.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Application</note>Let us conclude with the <hi>Shepheards</hi> on an <hi>Eamus,</hi> out of hand, <hi>ver.</hi> 15. Now, <hi>let us go to ſee the thing that is come to paſs, which the Lord hath made known unto us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seek</hi> the Lord whil'ſt he may be <hi>found,</hi> 55 <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 6. <hi>Call</hi> upon him whil'ſt he is <hi>near,</hi> and indeed this day <hi>he is not far from every one of us,</hi> 17 Acts 27.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59072:22"/>being in his Incarnation, God with us, <hi>in our nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God with us</hi> too in the <hi>Saeramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſigns,</hi> i. e. the Bread and the Wine, not much unlike (ſaith Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> in his Ser. of Nat. 12. pag. 118.) the <hi>ſign</hi> of <hi>this</hi> day, for what are they but <hi>weak</hi> &amp; <hi>beggarly Elements,</hi> 4 <hi>Gal.</hi> 13. in themſelves, yet in <hi>them,</hi> (as in the <hi>Cribb</hi>) we find <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſpiritually feed on his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. ch. 16.</p>
               <p>Nor could the Church, in her higheſt rapture, at this bleſſed <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> think on a fitter <hi>Anthem</hi> then that of this day to the <hi>Cratch.</hi> Suddenly on (the <hi>Infantem Jacentem in praeſepi</hi>) <hi>the Bahe in the Manger,</hi> follows, <hi>gloria in Excelſis, Glory be to God on high,</hi> &amp;c. v. 12, 13. who in his infinite love to mankind, brought Chriſt ſo <hi>low,</hi> to be <hi>partaker</hi> of <hi>our</hi> nature, that we might be partakers of <hi>his</hi> divine nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In hôc eſt charitas.</hi> Herein is love. This is a <hi>Feaſt</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> where Chriſt himſelf proffers himſelf to be <hi>fed</hi> on, and we agen love him ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59072:22"/>well, as to <hi>eat</hi> him, with a pious longing.</p>
               <p>We ought not to approach this <hi>Holy Table,</hi> without perfect <hi>love</hi> and <hi>charity,</hi> Love to <hi>God,</hi> to <hi>our ſelves,</hi> and love to <hi>one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Love to <hi>God,</hi> who when this <hi>fulneſs of time was come,</hi> ſent his <hi>Son,</hi> 4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. In this, <hi>was manifeſt the Love of God towards us,</hi> 1 Joh. 4. ch. 9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Love to <hi>our ſelves.</hi> Let us have a greater kindneſs for our nature, (ſince our <hi>Saviour Chriſt the Lord,</hi> hath vouchſafed to dwell therein) then to make it a ſink of luſts, and unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Love to <hi>one another,</hi> 1 Joh. 4 ch. 11. <hi>Beloved if God ſo loved us,</hi> (witneſs the place where he was found for us this day) <hi>we ought alſo to love one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus let us ſhew forth Gods praiſe for <hi>this day</hi> not only with our <hi>lips,</hi> but in our <hi>lives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This dayes <hi>Birth</hi> fills almoſt the whole Chapter, with <hi>wonder</hi> and <hi>thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving,</hi> verſes. 18.20.38. As we ſee
<pb facs="tcp:59072:23"/>in the <hi>Shepheards Anna,</hi> the <hi>Propheteſs,</hi> and <hi>all that heard it.</hi> Beſides, the <hi>Communion Canticle,</hi> (already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, learn't from the Angelical quire;) our Church borrows hence: Her conſtant <hi>Eveningſong</hi> of <hi>Nune Dimittis,</hi> from devout <hi>Simeon,</hi> v. 25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What ſhall I ſay? the praiſe hereof ſhall fill all <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>Eternity.</hi> Angels have begun to ſet us <hi>in.</hi> They are only concerned in this Joy, for <hi>our</hi> ſakes, 15 <hi>Luke</hi> 10. and ſhall not we for <hi>our ſelves?</hi> They cannot ſay, <hi>nobis</hi> to us; but <hi>vobis</hi> to you, <hi>natus eſt Salvator,</hi> is <hi>born</hi> this day a <hi>Saviour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what we muſt for <hi>ever</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, muſt we needs be ſo <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> as to forget <hi>this day,</hi> becauſe particularly ſet apart for this purpoſe?</p>
               <p>No. <hi>This day</hi> force up thy <hi>ſoul</hi> to an <hi>extraordinary</hi> pitch of <hi>praiſe,</hi> ſuch, as is not poſſible to keep it at every day.</p>
               <p>Now the Church will not leave out
<note n="†" place="margin">In the Communion Service.</note> 
                  <hi>Lift up your hearts,</hi> let us be as ready to anſwer <hi>we lift them up unto the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let us give thanks unto our Lord God. It is meet and right ſo to do.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:59072:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is very meet, right, and our bounden duty, that we ſhould at all times, and in all places give thanks unto thee O Lord, Holy Father, Almighty, Everlaſting God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Becauſe thou didſt give Jeſus Chriſt, thine only Son, to be born as on this day for us, who by the operation of the Holy Ghoſt, was made very man of the ſubſtance of the Virgin Mary his Mother, and that without ſpot of ſin to make us clean from all ſin.</hi> No leſs, <hi>is this Babe in the Manger: Therefore with Angels, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels, and with all the company of Heaven, we laud and magnifie thy glorious name,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:24"/>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:59072:24"/>
            <head>SECOND SERMON ON <hi>Aſh-Wedneſday,</hi> OR <hi>The Prevalency of Prayer and Faſting.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>17. Mat. 21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Howbeit this kind goeth not out, but by Prayer and Faſting.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IS <hi>Faſting</hi> one <hi>ſpecial means</hi> to <hi>caſt out Devils,</hi> and may it be rightly uſed as the <hi>only argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to <hi>prove</hi> a <hi>Demonia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k?</hi> 11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>Whether it be right to <hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> unto <hi>men,</hi> more than unto <hi>God, Judge
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59072:25"/>ye.</hi> Our <hi>Text</hi> is our <hi>Saviours</hi> plain and poſitive <hi>Aſſertion:</hi> The other but the diſcontented <hi>Vulgars</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vil, ſurmiſe and <hi>ſay ſo. John came neither eating nor drinking and they ſay he hath a Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We know the <hi>Devil</hi> prevailed over our firſt Parents, (a) <hi>Eating,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred <hi>Judas,</hi> after the <hi>(b) Sop;</hi> but he could effect nothing on Chriſt, <hi>(c) faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>hungry. (a)</hi> 3. <hi>Gen. (b)</hi> 13. <hi>Jo.</hi> 27. <hi>(c)</hi> 3. <hi>Mat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>(d) Fulneſs</hi> makes us moſt prone to <hi>deny God,</hi> and to <hi>forget</hi> him, and then you know whether we are like to fly. <hi>(d)</hi> 30. <hi>Pro.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Sinful and unclean exceſs feaſts <hi>Satan,</hi> intimated by the <hi>Evil ſpirits (e)</hi> impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunacy, to <hi>poſſeſs the greedy Swine. (e)</hi> 5. <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>In the words you may conſider two parts.
<note place="margin">In the words two parts.</note> 1. A <hi>Miſchievous Malady.</hi> 2. A <hi>main Remedy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">A miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous malady, and in this two things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in the evil ſpirits.</note> A Miſchievous Malady. <hi>This kind goeth not out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>main Remedy,</hi> but by <hi>Prayer and Faſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In the miſchievous Malady, you may obſerve in the evil ſpirits.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59072:25"/>
            <p n="1">1. Their <hi>Multiplicity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Their <hi>Malignancy,</hi> both are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in <hi>Hoc genus.</hi> This kind.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their Multiplicity. <hi>Hoc genus,
<note n="1" place="margin">Their Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity.</note> This kind,</hi> ſuppoſeth a numerous <hi>ſpecies</hi> or company of the <hi>dark Region.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To denote the <hi>multitude</hi> of <hi>powers,</hi> they are ſaid to make up a <hi>(f) Kingdom,</hi> a <hi>(g) Synagogue,</hi> a <hi>(h) Legion. (f)</hi> 11. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. <hi>(g)</hi> 3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. <hi>(h)</hi> 5. <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>The great <hi>Belzebub</hi> can command thouſands of his Miniſters (if God permit) to vex and trouble us: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that poor <hi>Gadaren</hi> ſo infeſted with this <hi>(i) helliſh</hi> Rout; <hi>we are many,</hi> may the chief Commander of thoſe forces ſeem to anſwer, in reſpect of thoſe that were in or about the poſſeſſed, <hi>(i)</hi> 5. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For though Chriſt rebuked the <hi>ſpirit</hi> whereby the perſon was principally actuated, in the <hi>(k)</hi> ſingular number, yet this <hi>Captain-agent</hi> was attended no doubt with a ſufficient rabble of the black Regiment, as appears by their ſeveral ſeizing (the word once given) on their ſeveral preys in that great <hi>herd,</hi> containing about <hi>(l) two thouſand, (k)</hi> 5. <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. <hi>(l) verſe</hi> 13.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:59072:26"/>
            <p>A <hi>multitude</hi> of <hi>Daemons</hi> (as one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) without violence to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, may lodge in the Body of one man; Theſe ſpirits being able to draw themſelves out of their uſual extent, into a far narrower compaſs; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps wholly to quit their own vehicle to make uſe of anothers; and ſo many may unite with the blood and ſpirits.</p>
            <p>But wherever this <hi>throng</hi> of Feinds did beſtow themſelves, whether in or about one man, Gods <hi>bounty</hi> was never the leſs in ſuffering them to poſſeſs no more; nor Chriſts <hi>power</hi> in driving them away from hence; the <hi>Devils</hi> being nothing the weaker, for not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing each one harneſſed with a ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral humane body.</p>
            <p>By what hath been ſaid, we may gather, there is a damned <hi>Militia;</hi> the <hi>Devils</hi> march about in <hi>Troops</hi> and <hi>Armies,</hi> to torment us, and conſpire our ruine; yet we know how to disband them all; no number of them can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>Prayer and Faſting. This kind goeth not out but by Prayer and Faſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:59072:26"/>
            <p n="2">2. In the malady,
<note n="2" place="margin">Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancy.</note> there is conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the evil ſpirits, as their Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, ſo Malignancy.</p>
            <p>Hoc genus. <hi>This kiud.</hi> As it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes a <hi>numerous</hi> Combination, ſo a Combination of more <hi>ſtiff</hi> and <hi>tenacious</hi> ſpirits. See Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi>'s Parapraſe on the place. Having a more ſtubborn <hi>(non egreditur, &amp; a vix diſcedit)</hi> goeth not forth, <hi>and a</hi> hard departing, (9. <hi>Luk.</hi> 40.) ſtamped on them.</p>
            <p>Hoc genus. <hi>This kind</hi> are noted for a ſort of bold, abuſive, moſt extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary fierce and cruel <hi>Devils.</hi> That va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued not a bare <hi>(n) Apoſtolical</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that ceaſed not to ſhew their malice, in the <hi>(o) face</hi> of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; <hi>(p) taring</hi> and bruiſing the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, making him <hi>foam, gnaſh with his teeth, pine away, (q) cry out ſuddenly, fall or wallow on the ground.</hi> Oft times caſting him into the <hi>fire,</hi> and into the <hi>waters,</hi> 9 <hi>Mark</hi> 23. Seeking <hi>Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> to deſtroy him, without the leaſt pity or reſpect on a <hi>(s) child,</hi> and an <hi>(t) onely child. (n)</hi> 9 <hi>Luk.</hi> 40. <hi>(o) ver.</hi> 42. <hi>(p)</hi> 9 <hi>Mar.</hi> 18. <hi>(q)</hi> 9 <hi>Luk.</hi> 39. <hi>(r)</hi> 9 <hi>Mar.</hi> 20. <hi>(s)</hi> 9 <hi>Mar.</hi> 21. <hi>(t)</hi> 9 <hi>Luk.</hi> 38.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:59072:27"/>
            <p>Now <hi>Hoc geuus,</hi> this kind, be their <hi>number</hi> never ſo <hi>great,</hi> their <hi>nature</hi> never ſo <hi>malign,</hi> is to be ejected Chriſts way, though no otherwiſe. <hi>This kind goeth not forth but by Prayer and Faſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">Remedy. Prayer and Faſting not to be ſevred</note> The Remedy, <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> not to be ſevered.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Becauſe <hi>Chriſt hath coupled them, and what God hath joyned together, let not man put aſunder,</hi> 19 Mat. 6.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. It was the <hi>Cuſtome</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of old, <hi>to Joyn</hi> them, as we ſee in <hi>(u) David,</hi> in <hi>(w) Eſther,</hi> the <hi>(x) Iſraelites, (y) Daniel,</hi> in <hi>Anna,</hi> 2 Luk. 37. So in the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> appointed for this day the <hi>Proclamation</hi> goes. <hi>(z) Sanctifie a Faſt, gather the People, and let the Prieſts ſay, ſpare thy people O Lord. (u)</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.22. 75 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13. <hi>(w)</hi> 4 <hi>Ch.</hi> 16. <hi>(x)</hi> 20 <hi>Judg.</hi> 26. <hi>(y)</hi> 10 <hi>Ch.</hi> 3. <hi>(z)</hi> 2 <hi>Joel</hi> 15, 16, 17.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. 'Tis the preſent <hi>practice of our Church.</hi> On our <hi>Wedneſdayes</hi> and <hi>Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, Dayes</hi> of <hi>Abſtinence</hi> (for the <hi>Bridegrooms taking away</hi>) (grounded on the command of our Saviour, ſee Mr. <hi>Browning</hi> on that text, <hi>p.</hi> 176, 177.)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59072:27"/>(2 <hi>Mark</hi> 20.) to his Diſciples that then they ſhould faſt in <hi>thoſe dayes</hi>) our Church enjoyns, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 12. <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Inſtant,</hi> earneſt Prayer, peculiarly applyed to the <hi>Letany, Id.</hi> p. 148. as the <hi>Eaſtern Church</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Becauſe (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> in his Paraphraſe on the text, <hi>Efficax eſt oratio praecedente Jejunio. Cyp. de Jejur. &amp; Tent. cap.</hi> 6.) Devotion in Prayer is apt to grow dull and faint, there muſt be an exerciſe of <hi>faſting</hi> and <hi>abſtinence,</hi> to ſet an <hi>edge</hi> upon it, and <hi>stir</hi> it up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer</hi> may prevail without <hi>Faſting,</hi> but <hi>Faſting</hi> without <hi>Prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>S. Chryſ. in Pſal.</hi> 145.</note> is to ſmall effect, and when they both joyn toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they make the ſtrongeſt aſſault on Heaven as can be.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the Servants of God, (in their higheſt concerns) would not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate them. 8 <hi>Ezr.</hi> 21.13 <hi>Act.</hi> 3.14 <hi>Act.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Faſting</hi> render us moſt <hi>acceptable</hi> unto God, and <hi>like</hi> unto the Angels.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:59072:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer</hi> (ſaith Reverend <hi>Hooker,
<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Prayer.</note> Eccl. Pol. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Papagr.</hi> 23. <hi>p.</hi> 23.) are thoſe <hi>Calves</hi> of mens <hi>lips,</hi> 14 <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3. Thoſe moſt gracious and ſweet <hi>odours,</hi> 5 <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. Thoſe rich preſents and gifts which being carried up into Heaven, do beſt teſtifie our dutiful affection, and are for the purchaſing of all favours at the hand of God, the moſt undoubted means we can uſe. And again a little further, the knowledge is ſmall (ſaith he) which we have on earth, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things which are done in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; notwithſtanding thus much we know, the Saints in Heaven that they <hi>Pray,</hi> and therefore <hi>Prayer</hi> being a work common to the Church as well <hi>Triumphant</hi> as <hi>militant,</hi> a work common unto men with Angels, what ſhould we think but ſo much of our lives is coeleſtial and divine, as we ſpend in the eyerciſe of <hi>Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So for <hi>Faſting</hi> (if it be right) is it not a <hi>choſen</hi> duty,
<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Faſting.</note> an <hi>acceptable</hi> time unto the Lord? 58 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4, 5.</p>
            <p>Again <hi>Faſting,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtome Ser. de Jejunio, Tom.</hi> 5. is an imitating or following the very Angels in Heaven,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59072:28"/>ſo far forth as we are able, <hi>&amp;c. Faſting</hi> is the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>Angels,</hi> ſo St. <hi>Ambroſe, Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>de Jejun. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 239. <hi>Qui jejunat Angelorum ritu vivit,</hi> &amp;c. St. <hi>Baſil Hom. de Jejun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe two now linked, muſt be of exceeding vertue and efficacy.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. <hi>Prayer</hi> from <hi>Faſting</hi> cannot be ſundred, for what is <hi>Faſting</hi> it ſelf, but <hi>ſilent Prayer?</hi> where in our <hi>Humility</hi> (without which vocal ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is but an empty ſound) God effectually reads our wiſhes, and the <hi>peices</hi> of a broken ſpirit, are to him pleaſing and prevalent <hi>Petitions,</hi> 51 <hi>Pſa.</hi> 17. A <hi>broken and a contrite heart O Lord thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My next buſineſs ſhall be to enquire why <hi>Faſting</hi> ſhould make <hi>Prayer</hi> ſo powerful? and Secondly,
<note place="margin">Why Faſting makes Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful.</note> what <hi>Faſting</hi> it is that doth ſo.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, <hi>Faſting</hi> makes our <hi>Prayer</hi> more powerful.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> 1. As it helps us to the greater <hi>watchfulneſs</hi> hereunto, ſobriety and this go together. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. c. 7. Our <hi>Vigils</hi> and <hi>Evenfaſts</hi> are all one. <hi>Fullreſs</hi> creates <hi>drowſineſs,</hi> we have an Eminent
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59072:29"/>inſtance of this in the Diſciples, 26 <hi>Mat.</hi> 40, 41.43. who after Supper, could not (would they never ſo fain) keep their Eyes open.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When the Belly is full,</hi> we uſe to ſay, <hi>the Bones are at reſt,</hi> we are indiſpoſed to any thing elſe, and this indiſpoſition of the <hi>fleſh</hi> (whilſt we are in the Body) hath too much influence on the <hi>ſoul,</hi> be it in it ſelf never ſo <hi>willing</hi> and well <hi>minded,</hi> 26 <hi>Mat.</hi> 41. 7 <hi>Rom.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Surfeiting</hi> degrades the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ody to a Beſtial ſluggiſhneſs, whilſt <hi>abſtinence</hi> (as much as in it lyes) advanceth it ſelf to the nature of a <hi>Soul,</hi> (a nobler ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance then to be nouriſhed by <hi>periſhing</hi> meats, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.27.) and makes it more ſuitable to that <hi>ſpiritual Body,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.44. wherewith ſhe ſhall be clad in Heaven, in order to a perfect vigorous and active devotion.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> 2. The more we <hi>deny</hi> our ſelves, the more God delights to <hi>own us,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. ch. 17. and our <hi>ſuit;</hi> and where can this be done better than <hi>by faſting?</hi> wherein we acknowledge our ſelves moſt unworthy of any of his bleſſings: This holy <hi>Juſticing</hi> our
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59072:29"/>ſelves, is a way to prevent Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. c. 31.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> 3. The ſence of <hi>want in Faſting</hi> makes us the more liable to pity others, and ſo the more capable of <hi>pity</hi> our ſelves, according to Chriſts gracious promiſe; <hi>Bleſſed are the merciful, for they ſhall receive mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> 4. <hi>Faſting</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Faſting is the Death of offences, the racing out of ſin.</hi> S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe <hi>in the place fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoted.</hi>
               </note> kills <hi>ſin,</hi> which ſets God and us at <hi>diſtance,</hi> 59 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. and <hi>ſtops</hi> his <hi>ears</hi> at our Prayers. The ſtarving the fleſh, is the mortifying our luſts.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>5</label> Laſtly, <hi>Faſting</hi> is the <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>utmoſt</hi> means we can uſe, to procure <hi>audience</hi> to our moſt earneſt <hi>requeſts</hi> amidſt our dreadfulleſt calamities, preſcribed by God himſelf, with a gracious promiſe of ſucceſs, 2 <hi>Joel</hi> 12. <hi>Turn ye unto me</hi> (ſaith he Lord) <hi>with faſting, and with weeping, and with mourning,</hi> &amp;c. verſe 18, 19. <hi>then will the Lord be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ealous for his Land, and pity his people, yea the Lord will anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ſome meaſure of miraculous <hi>faith,</hi> verſ. 20. together with an <hi>addreſs</hi> to <hi>Heaven,</hi> be not ſufficient to effect a conqueſt on the <hi>worſer Devils;</hi> all that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59072:30"/>is left to be added to theſe is <hi>Faſting,</hi> and that doth it. This <hi>kind goeth not forth but by Prayer and Faſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Religious Faſting. Conſiſts.</note> We come to ſhew what <hi>Faſting</hi> it is, that is ſo prevalent with Prayer, and that is a <hi>Religious Faſting.</hi> Conſiſting</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> 1. In <hi>abſtinence from bodily ſuſtenance,</hi> which is either, 1 <hi>Partial.</hi> 2. <hi>Total.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Partial,</hi> and here I mean not the <hi>Judaical</hi> diſtinction of meats, nor <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh</hi> niceneſs, nor <hi>Papiſtical</hi> Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, nor Heretical prohibitions, nor meer <hi>Phyſical</hi> or <hi>Political</hi> abſtinence for Healths ſake, or ſome <hi>civil</hi> intereſt, though theſe laſt ought indeed to be obſerved in reference to natural <hi>ſelf-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation,</hi> &amp; in <hi>obedience</hi> to juſt <hi>authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I mean a refraining from ſome delicate meats, ſuch as was <hi>Daniel</hi>'s <hi>Faſt,</hi> 10 c. 3. and <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſts, who in reſpect of his <hi>courſer diet,</hi> 3 <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. was ſaid to come, <hi>neither eating nor drinking.</hi> As if this Heavenly <hi>Preacher</hi> and <hi>pattern</hi> of penitency, this <hi>(vox clamantis in deſerto)</hi> this voice in the wilderneſs, (3 <hi>Mat.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4.) ſtood no more in need of corporal means, whereby to ſubſiſt, than (that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59072:30"/>pure <hi>procreation</hi> of the <hi>mind</hi>) the <hi>Voyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which abſtinence is to no other end than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pious <hi>Caſtigation</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> for the <hi>furtherance</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. c. 27. For the <hi>Inward</hi> man may be <hi>renewed,</hi> though the <hi>outward</hi> man <hi>decay;</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. c. 16. A weak Body may lodge a ſoul in good health and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous plight, as we ſee in <hi>Gailus</hi> Ep. Joh. 2. <hi>Faſting is a refreſhing of the Soul, the food of the mind.</hi> So St. <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Totall</hi> Abſtinence, is from all food whatever for a time, and this is either <hi>Extraordinary,</hi> ſeen in
<note n="(k)" place="margin">9 Deu. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes
<note n="(l)" place="margin">1 K. 19. ch. 18.</note> Elias,
<note n="(m)" place="margin">4 Mat. 2.</note> Chriſt;</hi> or <hi>Ordinary,</hi> poſſible to humane nature, ſuch as was <hi>Eſthers,</hi> 9 <hi>c.</hi> 16. This is the moſt compleat manner of <hi>Faſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It cannot enter into me, how deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves <hi>fleſh</hi> only, and gormon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing variety of <hi>Fiſh</hi> (moſt curiouſly and exactly Cook'd) with the beſt <hi>wines,</hi> &amp;c. can be counted <hi>Faſting,</hi> ſince we reckon theſe the moſt <hi>choice</hi> and <hi>courtly</hi> entertainments.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> 2. Religious Faſting, is an <hi>Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence</hi> from all <hi>pleaſure</hi> and ordinary <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> in this ſenſe we muſt ſanctifie a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59072:31"/>
               <hi>Faſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Joel</hi> 16. as the <hi>Sabboth.</hi> 20 <hi>Exod.</hi> 8, 9.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> 1. From <hi>pleaſure. Let the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom go forth of his Chamber, and the Bride out of her Cloſet.</hi> This muſt be a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Si ſela gu la peceavit, ſola Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>et &amp; ſufficit: ſi verò <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caverunt membra coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tora car n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Jejuneat &amp; ipſa?</hi> Bern. Ser. Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drag. 3.</note> 
               <hi>general</hi> penance to <hi>the Body,</hi> keeping the <hi>throat</hi> from its pleaſing <hi>meals:</hi> The <hi>Eyes</hi> (as at all times, ſo then eſpecially) from <hi>beholding vanity.</hi> The <hi>Ears</hi> from <hi>mirth</hi> and Muſick, the Body from caſe and bravery, we ſee this in <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Faſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. c. 16.20. who that while, <hi>lay on the Earth</hi> neither <hi>waſhed</hi> nor <hi>annointed</hi> himſelf, nor <hi>changed his apparel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> 2. <hi>Labour;</hi> Would we know what makes our Faſts ſlighted? Behold in the day of your faſt ye find <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> and exact all your <hi>labours.</hi> 58 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> 3. Religious Faſting, muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with works of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>mercy,</hi> 58. Iſaiah 6.7. <hi>Is not this the Faſt that I have choſen,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> 4. Religious Faſting is accompanied with a oynt and unanimous ſending up our <hi>praiſes</hi> to Heaven in a <hi>general Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> met together in the <hi>place</hi> of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59072:31"/>Gods <hi>publick</hi> worſhip, 1 <hi>Joel</hi> 14. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie ye a Faſt, gather the Elders and all the Inhabitants of the Land, into the houſe of the Lord your God.</hi> This noiſe rends the Heavens, and prevails with incomprehenſible Majeſty to take notice of our complainrs.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> 5. Religious Faſting muſt be accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with <hi>Repentance,</hi> and reſolution of a <hi>new life:</hi> All that we have ſaid is but a <hi>Mock-faſt</hi> without this. But the outward <hi>Ceremony,</hi> without the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> the <hi>Sign</hi> without the thing <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified;</hi> which doth but more diſpleaſe, as diſappointing the expectation, If there be no <hi>funeral,</hi> what means theſe <hi>mourning weeds?</hi> If no internal <hi>Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> what meant this ſpecious ſhew of it?</p>
            <p>Hence open <hi>prophaneſs</hi> is preſerred before ſecret <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi> The <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Harlots</hi> before <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phaeriſces,</hi> 21 <hi>Mat.</hi> 31.</p>
            <p>The Renting of the <hi>Heart,</hi> rather than <hi>the garments</hi> God looks at, and commands ſincere <hi>converſion</hi> with <hi>Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 2 <hi>Joel</hi> 12. Convertimini. <hi>Turn unto me with all your heart, and with Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:59072:32"/>
            <p>This <hi>godly ſorrow,</hi> intimated by our <hi>External humiliation;</hi> this <hi>ſorrow of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance not to be repented of,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. c. 10. <hi>Behold,</hi> verſ. 11. what <hi>Indignation</hi> it ought to work in us, yea what <hi>revenge</hi> againſt ſin, what <hi>carefulneſs,</hi> what <hi>fear</hi> of offending any more, yea what <hi>zeal,</hi> yes what <hi>vehement deſire</hi> of better obedience, that we may in all things <hi>be approved of God</hi> in our <hi>Faſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhewed you the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency</hi> of <hi>Faſting</hi> and the <hi>manner</hi> of it.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>Application.</head>
               <p>But methinks by this I he ar ſome ready to cry out, <hi>what doth this Babler mean?</hi> He hath been all this while do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſt nothing, <hi>nothing</hi> to his <hi>Text,</hi> for how doth he prove <hi>Fafting</hi> to caſt out <hi>Devils,</hi> and that the worſer ſort: as Chriſt <hi>here</hi> obſerves to his Diſciples ſaying, <hi>This kind goeth not forth but by Prayer and Faſting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer (without pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> miracles,
<note place="margin">In what ſenſe Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſts out Devils.</note> or <hi>Papiſtical praeſtigies) Prayer</hi> and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59072:32"/>
                  <hi>Fasting</hi> may be ſaid to caſt out <hi>Devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> (ſee Dr. <hi>Moor</hi>'s Myſt. of Godl. <hi>p.</hi> 116.)
<note place="margin">Sins are Devils.</note> makes that <hi>Legion</hi> of <hi>Devils</hi> 5. <hi>Mar.</hi> 9. to be no other than <hi>depraved affections,</hi> and Chriſt calls <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſuggeſtions</hi> in Peter, <hi>Satan,</hi> 16 <hi>Mat.</hi> 2, 3. And indeed to ſpeak the truth, <hi>Sin</hi> is worſe to us than <hi>Satan,</hi> for all the Devils in Hell, armed with their higheſt ſpight and malice, cannot hurt us without it.</p>
               <p>No doubt the <hi>Devil</hi> did encounter our Saviour, with as deſperate a deſign of <hi>envy</hi> as ever he did any; and to this end, (like an <hi>Innocent</hi> Bird in the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons of a rapacious <hi>Vulture</hi>) he was tranſported by him to as dangerous <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipices.</hi> The <hi>pinacle</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> 4 <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. and the <hi>exceeding high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> verſ. 8. yet had no power to <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief</hi> him, becauſe he could find nothing in him, 14 <hi>Jo.</hi> 30. he kept himſelf free from <hi>ſin,</hi> notwithſtanding thoſe <hi>many and ſtrong temptations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Lion</hi> may <hi>roar</hi> but he cannot <hi>rent,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. he may <hi>tempt</hi> but he cannot <hi>torture</hi> without <hi>Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:59072:33"/>
               <p>'Tis obſerveable in Dr. <hi>Moores</hi>'s Miſt. of Godl. <hi>p.</hi> 114. that the Jews <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> chiefly abounding in the Country of the <hi>Gadarens,</hi> made thoſe parts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove others ſo obnoxious, to be ſo cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly peſtered with the <hi>Infernal crue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſpeak proper, <hi>Sin</hi> is the only <hi>Devil</hi> to be condemned, for all our <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings</hi> from the <hi>Devil;</hi> for we look at the <hi>efficient</hi> not the <hi>instrument;</hi> it with much a doe can be eſteemed a <hi>cauſe</hi> in Philoſophie.</p>
               <p>In a Malefactor puniſhed, we nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blame the <hi>Judge</hi> nor <hi>Executioner,</hi> but the <hi>Offence;</hi> nor in the <hi>impious poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed,</hi> can we juſtlie inveigh againſt <hi>God,</hi> nor the <hi>Tormentors</hi> ſo much as the Tranſgreſſion.</p>
               <p>In this affliction, <hi>he</hi> cannot go beyond the bounds of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> 18 <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. nor <hi>they</hi> beyond their <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from him, <hi>Ep. Jud.</hi> 6. who hath <hi>reſerved</hi> them in <hi>Chains for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By all that hath been ſaid, I conclude, if <hi>Faſting</hi> kills <hi>ſin,</hi> as hath been ſhewed, it ſubdues <hi>Satan,</hi> and that in the worſt kind, <hi>Hoc genus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This kind</hi> goeth not out but by <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Faſting,</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:59072:33"/>
               <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">The Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure due to ſin, is a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering to Satan.</note> The Corrective <hi>Cenſure</hi> due to ſin, <hi>Excommunication,</hi> is a <hi>Delivering</hi> to <hi>Satan,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. c. 5. rendring men (as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex hôe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co decemur quòd eos qui ſegregan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; ab Eccleſiaſtieo corpore ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perantur, in vadit Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolus eos gratiâ deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titutos in veniens.</hi> Theod. in locum.</note> one obſerves) to have their bodies miſerably perplexed by him.</p>
               <p>Now what acquits us from this dreadful judgment but <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi> the neceſſarie <hi>Concomitants</hi> of true <hi>Repentance,</hi> 2 <hi>Joel</hi> 12, 13, 14. The only <hi>way</hi> to procure our <hi>pardon</hi> and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, 18 <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21, 22.</p>
               <p>The proper buſineſs of out Faſt <hi>this day</hi> begun, was in the primitive Church to <hi>receive</hi> the <hi>penitent,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Hiſt, Eccleſ. cap.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This day</hi> is ordered the <hi>Commination</hi> to be read, ſo full of <hi>threatnings</hi> to <hi>ſin,</hi> (whereto we all ſay <hi>Amen.) Invitations</hi> to <hi>repentance, proffers</hi> of <hi>mercie, Prayers</hi> for <hi>amendment,</hi> with ſolemn <hi>Faſting, Weeping,</hi> and <hi>Mourning,</hi> that I cannot but methinks rejoyce to ſee Satan here <hi>fall like lightning,</hi> 10 <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. and his <hi>works</hi> ſo abominated (my charitie gives me to believe) in this <hi>real</hi> Humiliation; where all that is in the world, 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 2.16. <hi>viz.</hi> The luſts of the Fleſh, the luſts of the Eie, and the pride of life; (the whole
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59072:34"/>temptations of the <hi>Prince of the world</hi>) lie buried in an Holie <hi>abſtinence</hi> from all <hi>ſumptuous</hi> fare, <hi>pleaſing</hi> ſighs, and <hi>gaie</hi> clothing.</p>
               <p>I ſhall offer but one conſideration more, to win the <hi>diſaffected</hi> I hope, to complie with our <hi>Church</hi> in the cuſtom of <hi>this Faſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though <hi>Repentance</hi> is alwaies requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, yet hath there not in all ages, upon occaſion, been daies wholly ſet <hi>apart</hi> for the ſolemn celebration hereof with <hi>publick Faſting?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And doth it not conſiſt in <hi>Regal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,</hi> to <hi>appoint</hi> thoſe daies? as we ſee in <hi>Ahab,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. c. 8. which <hi>Fast</hi> was proclaimed I doubt not but by a <hi>lawful power</hi> in him, though upon a <hi>falſ</hi> ground, and to an <hi>unlawful</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Namely <hi>made Blaſphemie,</hi> for the <hi>depriving</hi> him of his <hi>Vineyard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore <hi>when Civil</hi> and <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical</hi> commands concur in a <hi>general lawful Faſt,</hi> may we not harmleſly obey without asking <hi>why now!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet why not now? not only upon many <hi>civil</hi> deſigns <hi>uſeful,</hi> but upon many divine conſiderations <hi>ſuitable;</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:59072:34"/>now we may learn from the <hi>Crane, Swallow,</hi> and <hi>Turtle</hi> to know our proper ſeaſons of <hi>turning,</hi> 8 Jer. 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now,</hi> ſaith Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> all things <hi>turn;</hi> the <hi>year;</hi> from about this time, the <hi>new one</hi> takes date. In Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the <hi>Sun</hi> in its <hi>equinoctial</hi> line; the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> and all the conſtellations in it, do now <hi>turn</hi> about to the firſt point. The <hi>Earth</hi> and all her <hi>Plants</hi> now <hi>turn</hi> to their beſt <hi>ſplendor</hi> and <hi>delightſomneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Every thing thus <hi>turning,</hi> it would not be amiſs would it put <hi>man</hi> in mind of <hi>turning</hi> too unto the <hi>Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Joel</hi> 12. <hi>Therefore alſo,</hi> now <hi>ſaith the Lord, turn ye unto me with all your heart, with faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This time</hi> our Church religiouſly allots for <hi>a deep meditation</hi> on Chriſt's <hi>infinite paſſion,</hi> and the very thoughts of this bleſſed <hi>Bridegrooms taking away,</hi> aptlie fits us for a time of <hi>faſting</hi> and <hi>mourning,</hi> according to our Saviours in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, <hi>in thoſe daies ſhall ye faſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now,</hi> we are to <hi>look upon him, whom we have pierced,</hi> with a more <hi>earneſt</hi> and <hi>fixed</hi> eye, we cannot but <hi>mourn,</hi> and that <hi>bitterlie,</hi> (for our <hi>luſts</hi> which have
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59072:35"/>done it) without theſe, all the <hi>Devils</hi> in Hell could not, and therefore we muſt, I think, conclude <hi>theſe,</hi> the <hi>worſt;</hi> to <hi>tame</hi> which, Chriſt tells us, the only way in the Text, <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> this kind, <hi>goeth not forth but by</hi> Prayer <hi>and</hi> Faſting.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:59072:35"/>
            <head>THIRD SERMON ON <hi>Good-Friday,</hi> OR THE <hi>Paſsion of our Saviour.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>26 Mat. 39.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>O my Father if it be poſſible let this Cnp paſs from me: nevertheleſs not as I will but as thou wilt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS <hi>week</hi> was ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie called
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>By the Eaſtern Church:</hi> Magna &amp; Sancta <hi>Heb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. apud lat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Great week,</hi> every day whereof is marked with <hi>blood;</hi> the full Hiſtorie of our Saviours <hi>Paſſion;</hi> this the <hi>Church</hi> thought
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59072:36"/>fit, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> that it might ſink deeper into us, affect us nearer, wring us and ſting us more and ſtronger, till it makes <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſufferings in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ours, drawing from us, according to his <hi>Agonie ſweat,</hi> 21 Luk. 44. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Bloudy tears,</hi> Bloud and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in abundance, both from heart and eyes, making our <hi>morning</hi> ſome what ſuitable, to his <hi>Heavineſs and exceeding ſorrow of Soul;</hi> verſ. 37, 38. Our Prayers ſervent like thoſe <hi>ſtrong cries,</hi> 5 Heb. 7. which at ſome diſtance, in the dreadful ſence thereof, he ſent up proſtrate, for the removing (if it might be) of this bitter <hi>Cup. He fell on his face and Prayed ſaying, O my Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Our Text divides it ſelf into 2 parts.
<note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> 1. Chriſts <hi>Supplication.</hi> 2. <hi>Submiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Chriſts <hi>Supplication,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſts Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies three things.</note> wherein you have his earneſt Petition to God for the paſſing of this <hi>Cup,</hi> if poſſible, implying three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The Bitterneſs of the Cup.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Chriſts ſenſibleneſs hereof.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3.
<note n="1" place="margin">
                     <hi>The bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs of the Cup in</hi> 3 <hi>reſpects.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The difficultie of its paſſing.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The bitterneſs of the Cup,</hi> which appears, if you conſider.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:59072:36"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Cup it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Qualitie of the perſon,</hi> who was to drink it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The manner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conſider,</note> it was to be drank in.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider <hi>the Cup it ſelf,</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">
                  <hi>The Cup it ſelf; 'tis</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſts <hi>ſufferings</hi> are ſometimes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> 20 Mat. 22. <hi>a plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over head and ears;</hi> ſometimes to a <hi>Cup</hi> to denote the <hi>plentifulneſs</hi> of them. This <hi>Cup</hi> is wide and deep, and holds a great deal.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>This Cup,</hi>
               <note n="2" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which points at the <hi>grievouſneſs</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Cup,</hi> 75 Pſal. 8. is a <hi>Cup of red wine,</hi> (blood) <hi>full mixt,</hi> with the fierce wrath of God, 1 <hi>Lam.</hi> 12. for ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Cup,</hi> whoſo hath taſted but one <hi>ſup</hi> of it in the ſence of Gods <hi>frowns</hi> to his <hi>particular ſins,</hi> may perhaps gueſs ſomewhat of its inſufferableneſs to be drank <hi>clear off,</hi> for the <hi>ſins</hi> of the <hi>whole world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Cup,</hi> wherein is ſqueezed the whole <hi>vintage</hi> of Gods <hi>fury,</hi> due to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59072:37"/>the tranſgreſſions of all mankind, <hi>This cup</hi> muſt our <hi>Redeemer</hi> take down, dregs and all, as he becomes our <hi>Sponſor, to bear our griefs, and carry our ſorrows, God laying on him the iniquitie of us all.</hi> 55 Iſaiah 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This cup</hi> tranſmits moſt exquiſite tortures into his <hi>Bodie,</hi> unſpeakable pangs of <hi>Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Exquiſite tortures of Bodie.</hi> His <hi>head</hi> was digged with <hi>thorns,</hi> his <hi>back furrowed</hi> with the <hi>whip,</hi> 39 Pſal. 3. His <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>feet</hi> torn with <hi>vails,</hi> his <hi>ſide</hi> &amp; <hi>heart</hi> pierced with the <hi>Spear,</hi> for us he endures the <hi>painful, ſhameful, lingring, curſed</hi> death of the <hi>Croſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Unſpeakable pangs of Soul,</hi> witneſs that ſtrange diſtillation in the <hi>Garden,</hi> on the very thoughts of this <hi>cup,</hi> 22 Luk. 44. what wonderful inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 1 <hi>Lam.</hi> 13. <hi>fire in his bones,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding no doubt from the dreadful <hi>anguiſh</hi> of his <hi>Soul,</hi> 14 Mar. 34. cauſed in him this unheard of <hi>melting? A ſweat of great drops of blood</hi> ſhowring down his body, in a <hi>cold</hi> night, for they were feign to have a <hi>fire</hi> within, 22 <hi>Luke</hi> 55. whileſt he lay abroad
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59072:37"/>in the open air, upon the cold earth!</p>
            <p>At this hour what his <hi>ſeelings</hi> were, it is dangerous to define, ſaith Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> in his ſecond Sermon on the Paſſion, <hi>p.</hi> 354. we know them not, we may be too bold to determine them. In reſpect of theſe, the Greek Fathers crie out in their Liturgie, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>By thy unknown ſorrows and ſufferings felt by thee but not diſtinctly known by us, have mercy upon us and ſave us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such were the unſpeakable diſtreſſes,
<note n="*" place="margin">Urſin Cat. pag. 509. <hi>Though ſome expound it of his local deſcent thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> See <hi>Day</hi>'s L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. 7th. on the Creed, <hi>p.</hi> 140. 2. <hi>Conſider the perſon that drank this cup.</hi>
               </note> torments, and terrours of Chriſts ſoul, <hi>before,</hi> and then eſpecially when he hung on the Croſs, witneſs that dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful crie of <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me,</hi> 27 Mat. 46. that many make theſe that <hi>Hell</hi> (we ſay in our Creed) <hi>he deſcended into.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May not then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>This cup</hi> well make our Saviour crie out? <hi>O my Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>This Cup</hi> is aggravated by weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>perſon</hi> that was to drink it.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:59072:38"/>
            <p>For as is the <hi>perſon,</hi> (ſaith Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi>) ſo is the <hi>paſſion.</hi> Now Chriſt was the greateſt <hi>perſon</hi> that ever did or could ſuffer, and ſo likewiſe muſt his <hi>ſufferings</hi> be the greateſt, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>man,</hi> in himſelf altogether <hi>Innocent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Call it not immodeſty in her ſex, or only a ridiculous and ſuperſtitious credulity to an idle dream; (but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it rather to a good zeal raiſed in her by ſome extraordinarie Revelation) that <hi>Pilate</hi>'s Wife ſhould ſend ſuch a charge, in his behalf, to her Husband on the Bench, ſaying, <hi>have thou nothing to do with that Juſt man,</hi> 27 Mat. 19.</p>
            <p>'Twas nothing but what <hi>Pilate</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was convinced of, publickly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, <hi>he found no fault in him,</hi> 23 <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. no, nor yet <hi>Herod,</hi> ver, 15, no, nor the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf, 14 <hi>Jo.</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let him be Crucified</hi> lay the envious Rabble, nor can they ſhew any ſence for it, <hi>(why what evil hath he done?)</hi> but a raſh and lowder <hi>crucifigatur, let him be Crucified.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:59072:38"/>
            <p n="2">2. He was a <hi>noble Perſonage</hi> of the <hi>Race Royal,</hi> deſcended from Kings, 1 <hi>Mat.</hi> 2 <hi>Luke</hi> 4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He was, (and I can go no further) <hi>God himſelf:</hi> The <hi>creature</hi> ſo miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly Sympathizing, with its mighty <hi>Creatour,</hi> in that great <hi>Eclipſe</hi> and <hi>Earthquake</hi> at his <hi>paſſion,</hi> 27 <hi>Mat.</hi> 45, 51.54. makes the Centurion cry out, <hi>truly this was the Son of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Son of God</hi> in that ſenſe the Jews underſtood him, 10 <hi>Jo.</hi> 33.36. <hi>Equal with God,</hi> without any <hi>Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery,</hi> or <hi>Blaſphemous Preſumption</hi> at all.</p>
            <p>What will you ſay? did our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour then, did he ſuffer ſuch extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, he that was <hi>God</hi> himſelf? muſt the Lord of life and glory, in whoſe preſence, <hi>there is fulneſs of Joy,</hi> 16 <hi>Pſ.</hi> 11. ſubmit to a full draught of all <hi>Infamy, pain</hi> and <hi>death?</hi> 2 Phil. 6, 7, 8. If as the <hi>perſon</hi> is, the <hi>paſſion</hi> be, this argues again the bitterneſs of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>this cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of drinking this Cup.</note> The <hi>manner</hi> of drinking <hi>this cup</hi> aggravates its bitterneſs, as,</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:59072:39"/>
            <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">Unaccom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>naccompanied</hi> (alone) <hi>of the people there was none with him,</hi> 63 Iſa. 3. His deareſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſciples at this inſtant, they all <hi>forſook</hi> him and <hi>fled,</hi> v. 56. If <hi>Peter</hi> follovv, it ſhall be <hi>far enough off,</hi> v. 58. If he come into the Court vvhere his Maſter is arraigned, abuſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It ſhall be with a great deal of ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, proteſting with Oaths and Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, that <hi>he doth not know the man, v.</hi> 72.74. rather than by acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, to bring himſelf within the <hi>praemunire</hi> of this bitter <hi>cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">Unpitied.</note> 
               <hi>Unpitied,</hi> from that nature he took, and undertook for, <hi>(Man) They</hi> for whom he became <hi>bound,</hi> became his <hi>Executioners, They,</hi> for whom he <hi>drank</hi> this bitter <hi>cup, put it into his hands;</hi> among theſe a <hi>Table friend</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traies him, 13 <hi>Jo.</hi> 18. with as great pretence of kindneſs, a <hi>Hail Maſter,</hi> and <hi>a kiſs,</hi> v. 49.</p>
            <p>Had it been an <hi>Enemy</hi> had done this, 55 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12. it might have been <hi>borne</hi> but a (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Thou my <hi>fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar acquaintance,</hi> makes it intolerable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Man</hi> ſpares not his <hi>Saviour,</hi> but out of <hi>Spleen,</hi> 27 <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. and pure
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59072:39"/>
               <hi>ſpight crucifies</hi> him, and beyond all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, <hi>mocks</hi> and <hi>derides</hi> him, in the height of his pains on the <hi>Croſs,</hi> 27 <hi>Mat.</hi> 38, 39, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with <hi>Railing wagging their heads,</hi> and deſperate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, <hi>vah tu,</hi> 15 Mark 26. <hi>Ah thou wretch!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To him that is afflicted, pity ſhould be ſhewed,</hi> 6 Job 14. This yet affords ſome <hi>relief,</hi> when it cannot <hi>deliver;</hi> but on Barbariſm! as if ſome <hi>Savage Beaſt</hi> only were baited, not the <hi>Son of God</hi> ſuffering, here is <hi>inſulting</hi> and <hi>triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> all helping forward, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>this Cup,</hi> aggravating its bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt drinks <hi>this cup</hi> unpitied from God himſelf, as teſtifies the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned cry of <hi>Eli, Eli,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>My God, my God,</hi> &amp;c. Implying that <hi>God</hi> had for the time (ſhewing his extream an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger due to our ſins, which Chriſt now took upon him) withdrawn from him the ſence, and viſion of his comfortable preſence. <hi>Non ſolvit vnionem ſed ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traxit viſionem.</hi> Leo.</p>
            <p>The <hi>power</hi> of darkneſs is let looſe to afflict him: The <hi>Influence</hi> of comfort
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59072:40"/>reſtrained to relieve him, ſaith Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> in his 2 Ser. on the paſſion, <hi>pag.</hi> 356.</p>
            <p>St <hi>Auſtin,</hi> ibid. gives this reaſon why the Martyrs with ſuch courage, cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and ſinging, moſt of them paſſed through their torments. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>non eripuit ſed nunquid deſeruit? God delivered not his Martyrs, but did he forſake them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here the <hi>Father</hi> gives the <hi>Cup</hi> to his beloved <hi>Son,</hi> 18 <hi>Jo.</hi> 11. and leaves him with it. <hi>My God, my God,</hi> &amp;c. This makes the <hi>Croſs</hi> an inſupportable burthen, after this there is no living, but an immediate <hi>yielding up the Ghoſt,</hi> 27 Mat. 50.</p>
            <p>This, like the moſt <hi>groſs</hi> and <hi>deadly</hi> poyſon, lies at the <hi>bottom</hi> of the <hi>cup:</hi> at this diſmal and pitiful exclamation, the <hi>Sun ſwounds,</hi>
               <note n="2" place="margin">
                  <hi>What Chriſts ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibleneſs of the</hi> Cup, <hi>(implyed in his Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of it if poſſible) doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Earth trembles,</hi> the <hi>Rocks rent,</hi> the <hi>Temple flies aſunder,</hi> Jeſus expires.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſts Petition for the remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Cup,</hi> if poſſible, implies as the bitterneſs of it, ſo his great ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs hereof, to denote.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:59072:40"/>
            <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> 
               <hi>The Reality of Chriſts Humane nature,</hi> See Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi>'s Paraphraſe on the Text, <hi>That</hi> only was it, did ſhrink at this <hi>cup,</hi> for though Chriſt, <hi>God,</hi> ſuffered, yet it could not be as <hi>God.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> demonſtrates this at large, <hi>Sicut Philoſoph.</hi> &amp;c. Epiſt. 102. pag. 295.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſenſe of this <hi>cup,
<note n="2" place="margin">Sets forth Chriſts gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> did admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſet off the graces of Chriſt</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he became a pattern for our imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) in <hi>humility, patience, faith, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy,</hi> &amp;c. All theſe are more ſeen, when pain and affliction ſearcheth us ſo deep, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings us ſo vehemently, than when by any <hi>forced generoſity, ſtoutneſs of ſpirit,</hi> or any <hi>natural</hi> or <hi>Artificial helps</hi> whatſoever, we bear againſt the ſence thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">Argues the Reality of Chriſts ſufferings.</note> This <hi>ſence ſhews the Realitie of Chriſts ſufferings;</hi> for indeed without this they cannot properly be called <hi>ſufferings.</hi> They ſeem not much otherwiſe, than the <hi>ſcourging, piercing, crucifying</hi> of a <hi>ſenſeleſs</hi> body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This makes a greater endearment of Chriſts love to us.</hi>
               <note n="4" place="margin">This makes a greater endearment of Chriſts love to us.</note> The ſame that moves our <hi>pity,</hi> moves our <hi>love,</hi> now nothing
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59072:41"/>attracts our <hi>pity</hi> more to any perſon, than the conſideration of the moſt ſharp and ſevereſt ſufferings <hi>felt</hi> by him: The ſame <hi>draws</hi> a general love to Chriſt, when I am <hi>lifted up</hi> ſaith Chriſt, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his paſſion on the Croſs, <hi>I ſhall draw all men to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Love</hi> is the moſt forcible way both to <hi>win</hi> and <hi>continue</hi> a ſubject, hereby <hi>Chriſt</hi> enlargeth and eſtabliſheth his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and confounds the uglineſs, and deteſtableneſs of his uſurping Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titor, <hi>Satan,</hi> who, like a hard Maſter, exacts of his vaſſals cruel ſervices, <hi>cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſlaſhing, deſtroying</hi> themſelves. Whilſt our Saviour, like a gracious Prince, offers up <hi>himſelf</hi> a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for his people; ſubmitting himſelf for them to the moſt miſerable uſage of the vileſt and moſt malicious Miſcreants.</p>
            <p n="5">5.
<note n="5" place="margin">This ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of ſin.</note> The ſenſibleneſs of this <hi>cup argues the exceeding odiouſneſs of ſin:</hi> For this God <hi>ſpared not</hi> his own, only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, beloved <hi>Son,</hi> 8 <hi>Ro.</hi> 32. in whom with a miraculous <hi>voice from heaven</hi> he teſtifies, was all his <hi>joy, delight,</hi> and <hi>pleaſure,</hi> 3 Mat. 17.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:59072:41"/>
            <p>Is God angry with Sinners, do they ever feel the weight of his wrath? So muſt Chriſt himſelf, and that in the higheſt degree, as he becomes the greateſt ſinner in the world, by <hi>impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> 53 <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 6. for if he will be <hi>ſurety,</hi> he takes upon him the perſon of the <hi>debtor,</hi> and the <hi>debt</hi> is made <hi>his. Sin</hi> then muſt not be any ſlight or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable matter, which put the Son of God ſo to it. This ſhould work in us a greater indignation againſt it; our <hi>Riot</hi> and <hi>Exceſs</hi> brought him to this bitter <hi>Cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6.
<note n="6" place="margin">This Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies the damnation of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> The ſenſe of Chriſts ſufferings, <hi>makes the damned to Juſtifie God, in his terrible proceedings againſt them.</hi> They feel no worſe than what he hath already felt for them, and they ſlighted it.</p>
            <p>What God <hi>ſpared not</hi> in his <hi>Son</hi> can we expect him to bear within us? 'Tis true the <hi>merit</hi> of Chriſts <hi>ſufferings</hi> calls for remiſſion of our ſins, but on condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of repentance and amendment, <hi>Jeſus ſaves his people,</hi> not <hi>in,</hi> but <hi>from their ſins,</hi> 1 Mat. 21. we muſt be <hi>ſanctified</hi> if we hope for <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> by his <hi>blood,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. c. 30.5 Eph. 25, 26, 27. 1 Jo. 3 c. 2, 3.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59072:42"/>
            <p n="7">7.
<note n="7" place="margin">This gives us aſſurance of a perfect ſatisfaction by Chriſts ſufferings.</note> The ſenſe of Chriſts ſufferings, <hi>gives us the greater ſenſe of a full and compleat ſatisfaction thereby made to God for ſin.</hi> Sin hath already ſpit its <hi>utmoſt venom</hi> in that <hi>bitter cup</hi> which Chriſt ſo <hi>ſenſibly</hi> drank of. One <hi>drop</hi> of this <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> 20 Acts 28. cannot but make infinite attonement; what muſt whole <hi>ſtreams</hi> do ſo painfully ſhed?</p>
            <p>Chriſts <hi>blood</hi> hath a <hi>voice</hi> 12 <hi>Heb.</hi> 24. and every <hi>Groan</hi> a louder <hi>accent</hi> in it to cry for <hi>mercy.</hi> The more <hi>pain</hi> he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, the more <hi>pity</hi> and <hi>pardon</hi> he commands for us, whom God made a Saviour, <hi>perfect through ſufferings,</hi> 2 Heb. 10.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<note place="margin">Laſtly, This makes Chriſt ſenſible of our ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</note> The ſenſe of Chriſts ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>makes him experimentally ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ours,</hi> draws from him the greater compaſſion and ſuccour towards us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, 4 <hi>Heb.</hi> 15. 3 <hi>Heb.</hi> 18. We have not an high Prieſt <hi>that cannot be touched with the feeling of our Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> but one <hi>merciful</hi> and <hi>tender,</hi> the more ready to refreſh us in afflictions and death it ſelf, for thoſe <hi>ſighs</hi> and <hi>fears</hi> himſelf <hi>felt</hi> at the drinking of this <hi>bitter cup,</hi> which amazingly ſtartled
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59072:42"/>him and made him ſo earneſtly cry out <hi>O my Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Difficulty of the Cups paſſing,</hi> or indeed the impoſſibility of it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears,</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note n="3" place="margin">The Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of the cups paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</note> 
               <hi>From the unalterableneſs of Gods decrees,</hi> 2 Acts 22, 23. Could he not here have commanded twelve <hi>legions of Angels</hi> for his reſcue? 53, 54. verſes. But <hi>how</hi> then, <hi>ſhould the Scripture have been fulfilled that thus it muſt be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heaven and Earth may paſs away,</hi> ſooner than one <hi>jot</hi> or one <hi>tittle of Gods word fail,</hi> 5 <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. (one <hi>drop</hi> of this <hi>cup</hi> be ſpilt.)</p>
            <p>The ſtain of ſin cannot be waſhed off, but by <hi>blood,</hi> 9 Heb. 22. now what the <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>Bulls</hi> and of <hi>Goats</hi> could not do, the <hi>blood</hi> of the <hi>Son of God</hi> muſt. Thus it is written in the <hi>Volume</hi> of his Fathers <hi>everlaſting coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel,</hi> 10 <hi>Heb.</hi> 4, 5, 6. if you will too curiouſly enquire the reaſon, take St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> anſwer, <hi>Ipſum interroga me ſcire licet quòd ità, cur ità non licet: ask him, It is lawful for me to know it is ſo, not why.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:59072:43"/>
            <p>Notwithſtanding whatſoever hardſhip this beloved Son underwent <hi>in this cup,</hi> it argues the higheſt love of <hi>God</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, to <hi>ſuffer,</hi> and of <hi>him</hi> to <hi>drink it,</hi> and gives us all this cheerful confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that he who hath not <hi>withheld</hi> his <hi>Son,</hi> but <hi>delivered him up,</hi> in this manner for us, can with him deny us nothing, 8 <hi>Ro.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>Again Chriſts <hi>ſuffering</hi> on the Croſs, was ſuitable to mans <hi>ſinning; ut per l'g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num erigeret lapſum in ligno</hi> Theod. <hi>Ut fieret crucifixione quae erat genus mortis Maledictum maledictio pro nobis</hi> St. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, 3 Gal. 13. that as by the <hi>Tree</hi> came <hi>Death,</hi> by the <hi>ſame</hi> ſhould come <hi>life.</hi> That by his Crucifixion, which was a <hi>curſed</hi> kind of death, he might be made a <hi>curſe</hi> for us, to redeem us from the <hi>curſe</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> for it is written, <hi>Curſed is every one that hangeth on a Tree,</hi> 21 Deut. 23.</p>
            <p>Finally on the <hi>Croſs, extenſis utriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> manibus</hi> (as one obſerves) <hi>vocationem tàm gentium quàm Judaeorum ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caret,</hi> by ſtretching out of both arms at wideſt, he ſhews forth moſt gracious proffers of embracing both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:59072:43"/>
            <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">Chriſts ſubmiſſion.</note> In the text you have as Chriſts <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, O my Father,</hi> &amp;c. ſo his <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; Nevertheleſs, not as I will,
<note place="margin">What we learn in his Prayer.</note> but as thou wilt.</hi> Chriſt in his prayer tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth us, as</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Devout Geſture. <hi>He fell on his Face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Secrecy. <hi>He went a little further</hi> from his diſciples.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Watchfulneſs, verſe 38. <hi>Watch with me;</hi> fervency, in his <hi>Prayer</hi> he <hi>ſweat great drops of blood,</hi> 22 Luke 44. Frequency, he went away and prayed the <hi>ſecond</hi> and <hi>third</hi> time, <hi>v.</hi> 42.44.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Brevity and a form, the ſecond and third time, he ſaid the <hi>ſame words v.</hi> 42.44. which were not many.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. A Diligent liſtning for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of Prayer. Compare our Text with verſ. 42. whereas Chriſt here Prayes earneſtly, <hi>if it be poſſible,</hi> &amp;c. (as if he had had, ſome ſecret intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence from heaven, that <hi>it could not be</hi>) he alters it thus, <hi>ver.</hi> 42. <hi>O my Father if this Cup may not paſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Laſtly, He teacheth us holy, cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and humble reſignation of <hi>our</hi> will
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59072:44"/>to <hi>Gods</hi> will, for the anſwering our Petitions. <hi>Nevertheleſs not as I will, but what thou wilt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As Chriſt was God <hi>his</hi> will was not contrary to his <hi>Fathers,</hi> but as <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the <hi>Godhead is one, ſo alſo is the will of God.</hi> But the aſſumed na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſubject to humane infirmities, beginning to ſtartle at this <hi>cup,</hi> Chriſt will bring in ſubjection to Gods <hi>will.</hi> Since it is thy will <hi>(O my Father)</hi> in thine infinite wiſdom to order this <hi>cup</hi> for mans redemption. In <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>thee,</hi> and in <hi>love</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> I will freely drink it. It is a moſt terrible <hi>cup</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, witneſs thoſe ſtrange fears which poſſeſs me on the very thought of it, making me cry out <hi>O my Father, if it be poſſible,</hi> pity thy dear Son, and <hi>let it paſs! Nevertheleſs, not what I will,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the weak motions of my frail <hi>fleſh; but as thou wilt,</hi> according to thine eternal purpoſe, in the working of mans ſalvation, verſ. 42. <hi>If this cup may not paſs from me, except I drink it, Thy will be done.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:59072:44"/>
            <head>FOURTH SERMON ON <hi>Eaſter-Day,</hi> OR <hi>The Reſurrection.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>24 Luke 34.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Lord is riſen indeed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Primitive Chriſtians (I have heard) on this day, meeting in the morning, had this greeting: <hi>Some</hi> cryed, the <hi>Lord is riſen,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> anſwered, <hi>the Lord is Riſen indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What the early women had receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Angels, <hi>v.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6. and told to the Apoſtles, <hi>v.</hi> 9. and others; The two Diſciples from <hi>Emaus v.</hi> 13. now again ratifie &amp; declare to them for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59072:45"/>a moſt certain and very truth ſaying, <hi>The Lord is riſen indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of this report, which doubtleſs was with abundance of Joy, as witneſſes their great haſt <hi>v.</hi> 23. to bring it ſo many miles, <hi>v.</hi> 13. at night, <hi>v.</hi> 29, 30. late, after Supper) offers to our conſideration, <hi>two things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">In the text two things obſervable.</note> The <hi>Reality</hi> of Chriſts Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. 2. The <hi>benefit</hi> thereby.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</note> The <hi>Reality</hi> of Chriſts Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>The Lord is riſen indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some prejudiced Perſons, as they did all his other Actions, of caſting out Devils, feeding the multitudes in the wilderneſs, rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the dead, imput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe to ſome deluſion, Witchcraft, or Sorcerie; ſo they might miſconſtiue this of his Reſurrection alſo; and as they might ſay (as one obſerves in Dr. <hi>Moore</hi>'s Myſt. of Godlineſs, <hi>p.</hi> 138.) of that great Eclipſe of the Sun, at Chriſts Paſſion, that ſome deluſive ſpirits might intercept that light, in favour of him the great Magician, (whom they thought juſt to crucifie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thoſe two other Malefactors, <hi>quaſi latronum peſſimus</hi> (ſaith one) as the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59072:45"/>worſt of the three) the ſame might ſay, that the ſame ſpirits might open his Sepulchre, carry him away, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appear in his ſhape making uſe of his body to ſhew to <hi>Thomas,</hi> or ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own vehicles into the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of fleſh and bones, ſo that no mans ſenſe might diſcover any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. To this anſwers Dr. <hi>Moor</hi> in his Myſt. of Godl. <hi>p.</hi> 140. give me leave to rehearſe his own words, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not mend them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That which may be an Exception or Evaſion in any caſe, is of conſequence in no caſe;</hi> for what doth there at any time really happen, but evil ſpirits have a power to imitate ſo near, that our ſenſes may well be deceived?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Though they have this power in themſelves, yet I deny that they can exert it, when, and ſo far as they pleaſe,</hi> and therefore God would not permit them to add ſo irreſiſtable credit, to the whole Miniſtry of Chriſt, by this laſt miracle, if Chriſt had not really been the Meſſiah: but he being the Meſſiah, it was no deluſion of theirs, but a real tranſaction by that hand that is omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:59072:46"/>
            <p n="3">3. Let me add, <hi>The Devil that grand Politician of Hell would not be ſuch an enemy to himſelf, as to give Chriſtianity ſuch a huge advance, by counterfeiting the Reſurrection of Chriſt;</hi> eſpecially now, at ſuch a time; (when through the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Prophecies, concerning him, and his late Teſtimony of himſelf, in his life) all ſo expected it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Every thing look'd exactly like a real Reſurrection,</hi> 28 Mat. v. 2, 3, 4. The <hi>watch</hi> felt the <hi>Earthquake</hi> in their own fearful <hi>ſhaking,</hi> ſaw the <hi>Angel</hi> roll the Stone from the Sepulchre, 20 <hi>Jo.</hi> c. 21. <hi>Peter</hi> looks into the Sepulchre, finds no Body of Chriſt there. <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf immediately after <hi>appears</hi> to his Diſciples, <hi>eat</hi> and <hi>drank</hi> with them, they <hi>felt</hi> his fleſh, put their fingers into his wounds, what greater demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could there be to convince any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different men, of the <hi>reality</hi> of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Thoſe <hi>Miracles</hi> he did while he was alive, being ſo genuine and reall, as they were, muſt needs beget faith in the unprejudiced, that his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was real alſo, the ſame power in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59072:46"/>him, that raiſed <hi>Lazarus</hi> four dayes dead, 11 <hi>Jo.</hi> 39. could as eaſily raiſe himſelf, the third day.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,—<hi>Fas eſt ab hoſte doceri.</hi> His enemies <hi>falſe tale</hi> raiſed, 28 <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. to put off the belief of his Reſurrection, being ſo idle, and unlikely, gives us the greater perſwaſion of the truth of it. <hi>Say ye his Diſciples came by night and ſtole him away whileſt we ſlept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There muſt be good words, large money, <hi>v.</hi> 12. and a fair promiſe of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing their necks, <hi>v.</hi> 14. e're they can prevail with the Souldiers to blaze abroad ſuch an improbable ſtory.</p>
            <p>It was unlikely the watch ſhould ſleep, there being ſo ſevere a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the delinquents in this caſe. Say they did ſleep, how could they tell who ſtole him? or how could they once imagine it to be the Diſciples? What had they more courage for their Lord dead, than living? 26 <hi>Mat.</hi> 56. or if they were the Diſciples, vvhere do we read they were ever arraigned, and proſecuted for this notorious cheat? They were very merciful to forgive them that they were never guilty of.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:59072:47"/>
            <p>No, They ſecured the Sepulchre as it had been for their lives, <hi>rolling</hi> a ſtone before the door of it, ſo <hi>bigg,</hi> 16 <hi>Mar.</hi> 3, 4. no ordinary ſtrength could, ſo <hi>ſealed,</hi> 27 <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt durſt not remove it, till the Angels are commanded to become <hi>Porters</hi> to their riſing Lord, 28 <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. and Preachers of him to us, <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>He is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. The Lord is riſen indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> How comes it to paſs, the chief Prieſts and Rulers being ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily convicted of Chriſts Reſurrection from the Souldiers, 28 <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. did not yield to confeſs it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe they would rather baulk their Conſciences, than their reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the acknowledgement of ſo hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous an error.</p>
            <p>What a blurr had it been to them to have Crucified their <hi>Meſſiah</hi> with their own hands, had they owned him for ſuch? For had they known him ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> they would never have done it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8. now that ſuch <hi>knowing</hi> men ſhould not <hi>know</hi> him, you ſhall never know by their after-acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging him.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:59072:47"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Are we blind alſo?</hi> 9 Jo. 40. ſo ſticks in their ſtomach, they will not endure to hear it, and therefore having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ſo far in denying him, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to death, they cannot in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour draw back, but muſt deny him in his Reſurrection alſo, though never ſo plain and evident. <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rexit Domino verè. The Lord is riſen indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Obj.</hi> If the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d be riſen indeed, hath virally actuated that very body that lay in the Grave, what means his <hi>appearing</hi> and <hi>diſappearing</hi> at pleaſure, and coming to his Diſciples when the doors were ſhut? this is rather <hi>ſpirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,</hi> v. 37. than ſuitable to the nature of a <hi>real</hi> body, <hi>v.</hi> 39. <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>bones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt, ſaith Dr. <hi>Moor</hi> in his Myſt. of Godl. <hi>p.</hi> 141. gave a ſpecimen of a wonderful power reſiding in him in his transfiguration on the mount; and that he carried that about him then, that was able to ſwallow up mortality into life, though it was uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reſtrained as a light in a dark I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn. His Divinity therefore with his inward exalted humanity, I mean his Soul, took hold again of his Body, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59072:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>did vitally irradiate it, ſo that he was as naturally united with it, as any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel with his own vehicle, or any Soul of man, or any other Animal with their Bodies. Nor was it any greater won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Chriſt ſhould rarifie his body into a <hi>diſappearing</hi> tenuity, then that Angels and Spirits condenſate their vehicles, into the <hi>viſibility,</hi> and <hi>palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> of a Terreſtrial body, the ſame numerical matter ſtill remaining in both.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt hereby might diſcover the pure <hi>refined</hi> nature, and <hi>ſpiritual</hi> agility of our bodies after the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> when they ſhall be made <hi>like unto his glorious Body,</hi> 3 Phil. 21.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Chriſt hereby ſhewed he was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to be reſident with us in his corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral preſence;</hi> and ſo we to apprehend him by faith, not by ſence, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. ch. 26.</p>
            <p>Sometimes he appears and ſuffers himſelf to be handled by his Diſciples, to demonſtrate to their ſence the truth of his Reſurrection who were to be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous aſſerters, and infallible witneſſers of it to the world. Anon he withdraws,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59072:48"/>to exerciſe them and us in a ſpiritual apprehenſion of him inviſible. 11 <hi>Heb.</hi> 27. <hi>Bleſſed are they that have not ſeen, and yet have believed,</hi> 20 Joh. 29.</p>
            <p>So much now for the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Surrexit verè,</hi> the <hi>reality</hi> of Chriſts reſurrection. <hi>The Lord is riſen indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>benefit</hi> hereof follows, as</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>This convinceth us of his Deity,</hi> his <hi>Surrexit</hi> ſpeaks him to be <hi>Dominus,</hi> his being riſen, ſpeaks him to be the Lord; He is riſen indeed, he, and not another no man ever before him, 19 <hi>Jo.</hi> 41. lay in that tomb, and ſo was he raiſed too by his <hi>own power,</hi> not by <hi>anothers vertue;</hi> like him who revived at the touching of <hi>Eliſha's bonds,</hi> 2 K. 13. c. 21. 2 <hi>Jo.</hi> 19, 21. and 10 c. 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He is riſen indeed.</hi> His, was a <hi>real</hi> reſurrection from death, for they left him not, till they had his very
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>There is about mans heart (they ſay) a Skin called</hi> Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardium, <hi>containing in it water, which cools and moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens the heart, leſt it ſhould be ſcorched with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual motion, this skin once pierced man cannot live.</hi>
               </note> heart blood out, 19 <hi>Jo</hi> 34. no <hi>deluſive</hi> awakening from a Lethargie, or ſome ob-ſtupifying diſeaſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Reality</hi> of his reſurrection, proves the reality of his divine nature, in that he is riſen indeed, he is the Lord indeed; and ſo able to do infinitely for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59072:49"/>us, in delivering us from all evil, and repleniſhing us with all good things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Reality of Chriſts Reſurrection, is the only confirmation of our faith, in him to be the true Meſſiah,</hi> ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe 21. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his day decided him to be the <hi>Redeemer</hi> of Iſrael, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. c. 14.17. <hi>If Chriſt be not riſen then is our Preaching vain and your faith is vain alſo, ye are yet in your ſins,</hi> grievous conſequences; but the Lord is riſen indeed, and we may now ſtand under his arms, and make this bold challenge with the Apoſtle, 8 Ro. 38. <hi>who is he that condemneth? It is Chriſt that died, yea rather that is riſen again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Chriſts Reſurrection aſſures us of ours,</hi> 27 Mat. 53. after this, many dead bodies of the Saints appeared alive, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. c. 20. <hi>Now is Chriſt riſen from the dead and become the firſt fruits of them that ſlept; for ſince by man came death, by man came alſo the Reſurrection of the dead, for as in Adam all dye, even ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive.</hi> This is that joyful Anthem that welcomes in this Feſtival. Holy
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59072:49"/>
               <hi>Job</hi> ſeeing <hi>Eaſter,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> did <hi>Chriſtmas-day,</hi> 8 Jo. 56. (many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years before they were) by <hi>faith;</hi> cheerfully concludes <hi>his</hi> Reſurrection, from the Reſurrection of his <hi>Redeemer,</hi> 19 ch. 25. <hi>Victurum me certâ fide credo, liberâ vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e profiteor, quia Redemptor Meus reſurget, qui inter Impiorum manus occubuit;</hi> with aſſured faith I believe, and with free courage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that riſe I ſhall, in as much as my Redeemer ſhall riſe, who is to dye by the hands of wicked men; ſaith St. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> on theſe very words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eâdem catenâ revincta eſt Chriſti Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio &amp; noſtra.</hi> Chriſts Reſurrection and ours are linked with one and the ſame chain. If the <hi>Head</hi> be above the water, the <hi>members</hi> cannot periſh, otherwiſe they may, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. c. 16.17.</p>
            <p>Now we may inſult over death, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. ch. 55. ſince Chriſt riſen thence, hath given death it ſelf it's deaths wound, 13 <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14. <hi>O Death! I will be thy Death. Death</hi> now it ſelf hath its <hi>Epitaph,</hi> the <hi>Grave</hi> its <hi>Tomb-Stone.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:59072:50"/>
            <p>Nor is it a ſmall thing for Chriſtians to hear of their Reſurrection, ſince it is the Ground-work of all their hope, and happineſs, 1 <hi>Co.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 19. Our Souls are here burdened with a <hi>ſinful, ſickly, loathſome body;</hi> But at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, this <hi>corruptible</hi> ſhall put on <hi>incorruption,</hi> 1 Co. 15.53. this <hi>mortal</hi> ſhall put on <hi>immortality;</hi> this <hi>weak, diſhonourable</hi> duſt, ſhall be raiſed in <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> v. 43.</p>
            <p>Well may then be rehearſed with abundance of joy, a <hi>Surrexit Dominus, the Lord is riſen,</hi> ſince ſuch infinite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit doth ariſe to us from his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>Application.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is the Lord riſen indeed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Let us be riſen with him;</hi> Then is he riſen indeed to us, when our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are riſen with him, 3 <hi>Coloſs.</hi> 1, 2. Chriſts Reſurrection muſt work in us a Reſurrection to <hi>grace,</hi> 6 <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. before it can work for us a Reſurrection to <hi>Glory,</hi> 20 Rev. 6. <hi>Bleſſed and Holy is he, that hath part in the firſt Reſurrection,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59072:50"/>on whom the ſecond death ſhall have no power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Let us ſtrive to find Chriſt this day riſen;</hi> with the ſame <hi>haſte</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> 20. <hi>Jo.</hi> 3, 4. the ſame <hi>care,</hi> v. 11. <hi>conſtancy,</hi> and rapture of <hi>Joy,</hi> v. 16. as <hi>Mary;</hi> by the <hi>ſame means</hi> as the <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> in the verſe following our <hi>Text, viz.</hi> Breaking of Bread, in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Here we may with <hi>Thomas</hi> 20 <hi>Jo.</hi> 25. thruſt our hands into the print of the nails, and the wounds in his ſide to convince us of the truth of his Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>I know not; Our Church will not, at this time eſpecially, excuſe us from this duty; and cettainly the <hi>life</hi> every worthy Communicant finds in Chriſt (fed on here) cannot but ſufficiently inform him, <hi>that he is alive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And having thus found him, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be Glad, 20 <hi>Jo.</hi> 20. Glad, though Chriſts riſing, ſaith Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> in his 2 Ser. on the Reſur. <hi>p.</hi> 397. did no way concern us, or we that; yet 1. In that a Man, one of our own fleſh and blood hath gotten ſuch a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, even for Humanities ſake. 2. Then,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59072:51"/>that one that is Innocent, hath quit himſelf ſo well, for Innocencies ſake. 3. Thirdly, in that he hath foyled a common enemy, for amityes ſake. 4. Fourthly, in that he hath wiped away the <hi>Ignominie</hi> of his fall, with the <hi>glory</hi> of his Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng again, for Vertue and Valours ſake: for all theſe we have cauſe to rejoyce, but chiefly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce his Reſurrection was for us, 4 <hi>Ro.</hi> v. <hi>ult.</hi> how ought our ſouls to overflow with grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude?</p>
               <p>'Tis the peculiar faith of a Chriſtian to believe Chriſt Riſen, <hi>(Mortuum eſſe Chriſtum pagani etiam credunt, reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rexiſse verò, propriafides eſt Chriſtiano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. St. Auſtin)</hi> and the property peculiar to this faith to create in us Joy, for his Reſurrection. Lord we believe, help thou our unbelief.</p>
               <p>O Heavenly Father, who didſt raiſe thy Son from death, raiſe our dull Souls to a due thankfulneſs, for this mercy!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is meet, right, and our bounden du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that we ſhould at all times, and in all places, give thanks unto thee, Almighty Everlaſting God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:59072:51"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>But chiefly are we bound to praiſe thee for the glorious Reſurrection of thy Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord: for he is the very Paſchal Lamb that was offered for us, and hath taken away the Sin of the world, who by his death hath deſtroyed death, and by his Riſing to life, hath reſtored to us everlaſting life. Therefore with Angels, and Archangels, and with all the company of Heaven, we land and magnifie thy glorious name evermore praiſing thee, and ſaying, Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God of Hoſts, Heaven and Earth are full of thy glory. Glory be to thee O Lord moſt High.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:59072:52"/>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:59072:52"/>
            <head>FIFTH SERMON ON <hi>Holy-Thurſday,</hi> OR <hi>The Aſcenſion.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>4 Epheſ. 10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He that deſcended, is the ſame alſo that aſcended up, far above all Heavens, that he might fill all things.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HERE is the <hi>Higheſt aſcent</hi> anſwering to the <hi>Loweſt deſcent</hi> immagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and <hi>both</hi> in one and the ſame perſon. <hi>He that deſcended, is the ſame alſo that aſcended,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:59072:53"/>
            <p>This the Apoſtle ſpeaks of Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8. in his Expoſition on that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical Pſalm the 68. proper for this day.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Deſcent</hi> we have already treated, from Heaven to the Earth, the loweſt part of the world, at his <hi>Incarnation;</hi> from the ſurface of the Earth, into the Bowels thereof (the grave) at his <hi>paſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He deſcended from the boſome of his Eternal Father (that excellent Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. c. 17.) into the lap of a poor Virgin: He that thought it no robbery to be equal with God, took to him humane nature and in it the form of a Servant, ſubmitted himſelf to ſhame pain, mortality, was Crucified, Dead, and Buried, nay (ſay we in our Creed) <hi>Deſcended into Hell;</hi> lower than this he could not go.</p>
            <p>Now He that <hi>deſcended</hi> thus, hath as many lifts of his <hi>aſcenſion</hi> till he came to the higheſt pitch can be, Mark, the tearms of his riſe, He aſcended <hi>up, far, above, all Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:59072:53"/>
            <p>In the Text. you have three parts,
<note place="margin">Diviſion. In the Text three things.</note>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The <hi>Perſon Aſcending.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Aſcent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The <hi>End of it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Perſon Aſcending.</hi> He that <hi>deſcended, ipſe eſt,</hi> is the ſame alſo that <hi>aſcended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>aſcent, longè ſupra omnes caelos,</hi> up far above all heavens.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>End</hi> of it. <hi>That he might fill all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Perſon aſcending.</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoa Aſcead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> He that deſcended, is the ſame alſo that aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The ſame Perſon, with the ſame Body, though now made immortal, Glorious, 3 <hi>Phil.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Viſne in altum ſcandere, Humilitas Gradus eſt.</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) St. <hi>Paul</hi> here ſhews the way and manner of Chriſts Aſcending (which muſt be ours) by <hi>Deſcending</hi> firſt, <hi>v.</hi> 9. He makes his deep <hi>Humiliation</hi> the cauſe of his <hi>Exaltation,</hi> 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> 8, 9. He <hi>humbled</hi> himſelf unto death, even the death of the Croſs, wherefore God alſo hath <hi>highly exalted</hi> him.</p>
            <p>Mans nature is aſpiring and aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, loves to be uppermoſt, 23 <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.7.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59072:54"/>This we find not only in the Scribes and Phariſees, but in the Diſciples themſelves, <hi>altum ſapimus omnes,</hi> all would be above: would we know the right way? It is by <hi>deſcending,</hi> coming down firſt, <hi>He that humbleth himſelf ſhall be exalted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſcending</hi> before <hi>Deſcending</hi> is <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical</hi> and <hi>dangerous,</hi> this made Angels Devils, <hi>Ep. Jud.</hi> 6. ruined our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, 3 <hi>Gen. He that exalteth himſelf ſhall be abaſed,</hi> 23 Mat. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pride</hi> being our <hi>fall</hi> the only way of <hi>recovering</hi> our ſelves is <hi>Humility,</hi> 20 <hi>Mat.</hi> 26, 27. whereof Chriſt gives him an Example, 13 <hi>Joh.</hi> 13, 14, 15. who is there very diligent with his Towel and his Baſon, waſhing his Diſciples feet, lower he could not well ſtoop.</p>
            <p>It argues too much <hi>ſenſuality</hi> and <hi>Carnality</hi> to be (with <hi>Zebedee</hi>'s Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) 20 <hi>Mat.</hi> v. 21, 22. all upon <hi>raigning,</hi> without any thought of <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction:</hi> The way to Heaven is through tribulation, to eternal life, through death, 24 <hi>Luke</hi> 26. If we would come where the Captain of our Salvation is
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59072:54"/>arrived, we muſt tread in the ſame ſteps, <hi>ſufferings:</hi> The <hi>Servant</hi> is not <hi>greater</hi> than his <hi>Lord,</hi> 20 <hi>Jo.</hi> 16. and therefore ſhould be content with the ſame faſhion of <hi>Aſcending,</hi> by <hi>Deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. He that deſcended,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>Deſcending</hi> (the lower it is) <hi>puts the greater admiration and luſtre on Aſcending;</hi> Motions ſlow and gradual, (as in a Dial) the leſs or no notice can be taken of them, they are not perceptible; but thoſe which are ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and aloft are gazed on, with the more delight and wonder. A rich heir apparent to the Crown, advanced ſtrait to his lawful Throne, cauſeth not ſuch aſtoniſhment as when taken from the worſt and baſeſt condition. This demonſtrates incomparable Might and Excellency to effect. 113 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Who is like the Lord our God? he raiſeth the poor out of the duſt, and the needy out of the Dunghill, that he may ſet him with</hi> Princes, <hi>even with the</hi> Princes.</p>
            <p>(The <hi>Aſcent,</hi> being conſidered in reference to the <hi>Deſcent,</hi>) the lower the Deſcent hath digged, the higher muſt neceſſarily the Aſcent be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59072:55"/>from it. Now our Creed brings Chriſts <hi>Deſcent,</hi> as far as <hi>Hell,</hi> the better preſently to amplifie his <hi>Aſcent</hi> into <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that <hi>deſcended</hi> thither, is the ſame (ſaith the Apoſtle) that <hi>aſcended</hi> up, far above all Heavens; which brings me to</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">Chriſts Aſcent.</note> The <hi>Aſcent,</hi> up far above all Heavens.</p>
            <p>This <hi>going up on high,</hi> 68 Pſal. 18. whence St. <hi>Paul</hi> here quotes his Aſcent, will (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> in his 7th. Sermon on <hi>Whitſun.</hi> p. 668.) bear fair ſences. It may be interpreted of <hi>Moſes Aſcending</hi> up into Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> in the <hi>literal ſenſe.</hi> 2. Of <hi>Davids Aſcending</hi> up with the Ark into Mount <hi>Sion</hi> in the <hi>Analogical ſence,</hi> 2 Sam. 5 ch. 3. Of <hi>Gods triumphing</hi> over his Churches enemies, in the <hi>Moral ſence.</hi> Or 4. Of <hi>Chriſts Aſcending in a Prophetical ſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>this</hi> Aſcent excells all the other, 'tis higher than <hi>Sinai</hi> or <hi>Sion,</hi> no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon deliverance. 'Tis not only ſome high mountain as they thought of <hi>Elias.</hi> (2 K 2. c. 16. <hi>Pelion upon Oſſa</hi> will not reach it, 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> above the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59072:55"/>
               <hi>quite out of Sight,</hi> 1 Acts 9. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ab</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>video dicitur,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Above all Heavens,</hi> even the very higheſt of them.</p>
            <p>Here we ſhall paſs by (as not worthy our ſtay) the <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> of ſome perſons who (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Beza</hi> obſerves) denying <hi>ſupra coelos eſse locum</hi> that there is any place above the Heavens, would attribute to Chriſt, <hi>Corpus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Body not <hi>circumſcribed,</hi> and ſo <hi>unbody</hi> his <hi>Body</hi> (as I may ſay) aſcribing to it (the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of a divine Eſſence only) <hi>omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſence:</hi> would not this ſomewhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend <hi>Tranſubſtantiation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to deny Chriſt
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Niſi ſit Chriſtus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalis homo feuſtra ſperamus quod ſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> Beza <hi>in Textum.</hi>
               </note> pure and perfect man, (which we muſt do,) if we thus wrong him of his <hi>Hamane Body,</hi> were <hi>Spem noſtram à fundamentis convellere</hi> So <hi>Beza.</hi> To deſtroy the foundation of all our Chriſtian hope.</p>
            <p>With the ſame <hi>Body</hi> that was <hi>paſſive, buffetted, bruiſed, buried,</hi> with the ſame <hi>Body</hi> material, <hi>(fleſh and bones)</hi> organi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, palpable, viſible, 24 <hi>Luk.</hi> 29. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> ſaith Chriſt by all this, <hi>It is</hi> Ipſe Ego, <hi>I my ſelf) He aſcended up, far above all Heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:59072:56"/>
            <p>The ſame that after his Reſurrection, retained the <hi>Print of the Nails,</hi> and the wound of the <hi>Spear</hi> in his <hi>Side,</hi> 20 <hi>Jo.</hi> 2.7. is by him carried up into Heaven, <hi>where he is ſet down, with it, on the right hand of God,</hi> i. e. Enthroned by his immediate divine <hi>Shechina,</hi> or that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable unimitable Glory God doth in a moſt peculiar manner manifeſt there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtum ſcimus verum hominem fuiſſe, nec eſſe diſiſſe, ac pro indè finitnm corpus, finitam animam habere, ſcimus in coelos aſcendiſſe gloriae Patris ſocium,</hi> &amp;c. Beza.</p>
            <p>So much for the Aſcent.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">The end of Chriſts Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending.</note> We come to the en dof Chriſts Aſcending, <hi>viz. That he might fill all things.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifies to <hi>fulfil:</hi> That he might <hi>fulfill</hi> all that was foreſaid of him, and all that is or ſhould be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for the full glorification of the Church. So Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> in his Paraph. on the Text.</p>
            <p>The cauſes then of his <hi>Aſcending</hi> were,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To lead Captivity Captive,</hi> v. 8. Sin, Satan, Death and the Grave. He riding in triumph into <hi>Heaven,</hi> like a glorious <hi>Victor,</hi> made an open ſhew of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59072:56"/>theſe <hi>ſpoils,</hi> 2 <hi>Col.</hi> 15. diſarming <hi>Sin</hi> of its <hi>condemning</hi> power, 8 <hi>Ro.</hi> 3. cancelled the terrible <hi>Hand-writing</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> that was <hi>againſt us,</hi> 2 <hi>Col.</hi> 14. ſlew <hi>Death</hi> by being ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in by it, He trod out the <hi>ſting</hi> of this <hi>Adder,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 55. 91 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13. He trambled on the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> 12 <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. <hi>Bruiſing his head</hi> with his victorious <hi>Heel.</hi> 3 <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>To give Gifts unto men.</hi> The <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> Act ſpoke the <hi>valour</hi> of his <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, This the Bounty,</hi> that, ſhewed his <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> this, his <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> v. 8. <hi>When He aſcended up on High, He led Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity Captive, and gave Gifts unto men.</hi> This day of his <hi>Coronation,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits run with <hi>Wine,</hi> the new <hi>Coyne</hi> is ſcattered abroad.</p>
            <p>When he was <hi>taken out of Sight,</hi> 1 <hi>Acts</hi> 9. eſpecially, at ſuch a diſtance, <hi>up far above all Heavens,</hi> we might have been apt to have concluded, <hi>out of ſight out of mind,</hi> Pharaohs <hi>chief Butlers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advance</hi> made him <hi>forget Joſeph,</hi> 3 Gen. 13, 14.23. But the <hi>height of</hi> Chriſts place, doth not make him unmindful of us, he <hi>remembers</hi> us in his <hi>Kingdom,</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:59072:57"/>23 <hi>Luke</hi> 42. and from thence ſends us rich <hi>preſents</hi> gifts, and graces, Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Spiritual bleſſings, 1 <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. for whatever we receive as a pledge of Gods greateſt love towards us muſt be through his mercy in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>To prepare a place for all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him,</hi> 14 <hi>Jo.</hi> 1, 2. This bleſſed <hi>Harbinger,</hi> 6 <hi>Heb.</hi> 20. is gone before in our fleſh, to take <hi>poſseſſion</hi> for us of our <hi>Heavenly Manſions,</hi> moſt <hi>glorious</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, and <hi>Magnificent,</hi> as provided and appointed by ſuch Infinite <hi>Majeſty</hi> and <hi>Bounty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prepare</hi> us dear Jeſus, for thoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py habitations which thy love hath ſo painfully and carefully fitted and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for us.</p>
            <p>The Relation that is betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>heaven,</hi> and his <hi>Church</hi> on <hi>earth,</hi> gives us a full aſſurance that he will bring that thither.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Head</hi> is not compleat without its <hi>members,</hi> 5 <hi>Eph.</hi> 23. nor the <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom</hi> without his <hi>Bride,</hi> 2 <hi>Mar.</hi> 19, 20. <hi>Chriſt</hi> therefore ſhall undoubtedly unite to himſelf his <hi>Body Mystical,</hi> and take to the ſame <hi>place</hi> his beloved
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59072:57"/>beauteous <hi>Spouſe; She ſhall be brought to the King (her Husband) in raiment of needle-work, with gladneſs and rejoycing ſhall ſhe be brought into the Kings Palace.</hi> 45 Pſal. 14, 15.</p>
            <p>What Chriſt prayes for 17 <hi>Joh.</hi> 24. himſelf is alſo able to perform, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e're the <hi>man</hi> dwells he may Command his <hi>wife</hi>) none can detain the <hi>Church</hi> from cohabiting with her <hi>Lord</hi> in Heaven.</p>
            <p>As all Chriſts undertakings in the fleſh, his <hi>Birth, Death, Reſurrection,</hi> he was <hi>Born</hi> for us, 9 Iſa. 6. 2 Luk. 11. <hi>Dyed</hi> for us, 4 <hi>Ro.</hi> 25. <hi>Roſe</hi> again for us; ſo at his <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> we come in too, he <hi>aſcended</hi> for us, <hi>he is gone up on high far above all Heavens</hi> to prepare there a place for us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>To ſend the Comforter down unto his Church,</hi> 16 Jo. 7. <hi>It is expedient for you,</hi> &amp;c. There lyes an expedience that <hi>Holy Thurſday</hi> ſhould preceed <hi>Pentecoſt;</hi> Chriſt muſt <hi>go</hi> before the Holy Ghoſt can <hi>come</hi> down; for which Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> alledges excellent Reaſons gathered from the fathers.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:59072:58"/>
            <p n="1">1. On the <hi>Holy Ghoſts</hi> part, who came to manifeſt himſelf as God; by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gns and wonders, now had Chriſt ſtayed, they might have att<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted theſe to him, which had been an <hi>impeachment</hi> of the others <hi>divinity,</hi> but <hi>Chriſt aſcending,</hi> all ſuch immaginations ceaſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. On <hi>Chriſts</hi> part. A little im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment it might have been to Chriſts <hi>equality</hi> to the <hi>Father;</hi> for he not going to ſend him, but ſtaying ſtill here till he was ſent; the <hi>ſending</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> might have been aſcribed to the <hi>Father</hi> alone, as his ſole act; That he had been ſent for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake had been the moſt; but being <hi>aſcended,</hi> his love and power is apparent to be equal with the Father in <hi>ſending</hi> him, and we alike beholding to them both. Now, the <hi>Fathers ſending</hi> him, 14 <hi>Jo.</hi> 26. and the <hi>Sons ſending</hi> him from the <hi>Father,</hi> 15 <hi>Jo.</hi> 26. is all one.</p>
            <p n="3">3. On <hi>our</hi> part, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>that he might fill all things,</hi> by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> (which he could not by his <hi>Body</hi>) that he might be preſent with every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular member of his diſperſed Church;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59072:58"/>thus is he with all Chriſtians in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, at all times even unto the end of the world, 28 <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. See <hi>Piſcator</hi> on the Text, <hi>Hoc Sophiſtae Ubiquitar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſic exponunt, quaſi diceret</hi> Paulus: <hi>ut omnia loca impleret ſuo corpore. Sed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolus ſe ipſe declarat duobus verſibus ſequentibus ex quorum Collatione perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur, Apoſtolum hoc velle dicere Chriſtum aſcendiſſe in coelum ut indè miſſo ſpiritu ſancto, impleret illius donis omnia Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae membra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, (ſay they) Chriſt withdrew his <hi>Bodily</hi> preſence, to draw us off from ſence or fleſhly fondneſs of him, which his neareſt and deareſt followers were too much prone to, as we ſee in <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> 11 <hi>Jo.</hi> 21. attributing the greateſt power to his <hi>Corporal</hi> reſidence. <hi>Lord if thou hadſt been here, my Brother had not dyed.</hi> As if <hi>abſent</hi> he had not been able to have prevented it. The <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> are upon <hi>building</hi> of <hi>Tabernacles</hi> for his ſtay in the <hi>fleſh.</hi> As if in <hi>that</hi> only conſiſted the <hi>Co ſummation</hi> of their <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs,</hi> 17 <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. <hi>Mary</hi> would fain be embracing him with a carnal contract, 20 <hi>Jo.</hi> 17. which Chriſt ſtrives to beat
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59072:59"/>her off from, with a <hi>Noli me tangere, touch me not,</hi> putting her in mind nere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon of his <hi>Aſcenſion.</hi> After that he ſends his <hi>Spirit,</hi> whereby we are to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him ſpiritually; <hi>Seeing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible</hi> by <hi>faith,</hi> (which the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e abſtract from <hi>ſence</hi>) the more notable bleſſing it hath pronounced to it, 20 <hi>Jo.</hi> 29. <hi>Bleſſed are they hat have not ſeen, and yet have believed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, The <hi>Fathers</hi> ſtick not to ſay, that at <hi>Chriſts Aſcenſion,</hi> before the <hi>Coming</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that he ſhould withdraw himſelf (for ſome time as to his <hi>Bodily</hi>) ſo his <hi>Spiritual</hi> preſence likewiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Diſciples</hi> growing faint and <hi>tepid</hi> (whilſt he was with them) ſhould now become more <hi>vigilant</hi> and <hi>watchful</hi> after him, on the ſenſe of the loſs of him, like the <hi>Spouſe,</hi> 5 <hi>Cant.</hi> 2, 3, 5, 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they might grow leſs <hi>carnally ſecure</hi> in their thoughts of <hi>keeping</hi> him, who were apt to preſume upon a <hi>non moveber,</hi> 30 Pſal. 7. <hi>a never be moved, though I dye with thee will I not deny thee,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> 26 Mat. 35. <hi>and all
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59072:59"/>the reſt,</hi> yet we find the contrary, <hi>v.</hi> 56.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The conſideration hereof, as alſo the ſence of their neceſſary falling into ſin (without Chriſts Spiritual preſence) drives them to humility a fit <hi>poſture to invite the Holy Ghoſts Deſcent and abode,</hi> 57. Iſai. 15.</p>
            <p>Thus, <hi>Chriſtus abit, ut Paracletus veniat. Chriſt is gone up on high, far above all Heavens</hi> to ſend his <hi>Spirit</hi> down on Earth, even the <hi>loweſt</hi> among men.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>To appear in the ſight of God to interceed for us.</hi> 9 Heb. 24. 8 Ro. 34. &amp;c. 1 Jo. 2. c. 1. 8 Rev. 3. Now we may come with <hi>boldneſs unto the Throne of grace,</hi> 4 Heb. <hi>ult.</hi> ſince we h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve ſuch a <hi>prevailing friend</hi> in the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; whatſoever you ſhall ask the Father, in my name, he ſhall give it you,</hi> 16 <hi>Jo.</hi> 22. <hi>Bleſſed Jeſus!</hi> we will not robb thee of thy <hi>Mediatorſhip,</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed for us ſtill, as thou didſt once on earth, 17 <hi>Jo.</hi> 23. <hi>That where thou art, there we may be alſo,</hi> whil'ſt we are here, let our Souls, <hi>our affections be above,</hi> 3 <hi>Col.</hi> 2. and hereafter receive us, both <hi>Souls</hi> and <hi>Bodies,</hi> unto that unſpeakable
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59072:60"/>
               <hi>glory,</hi> thou now enjoyeſt with thy <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> where thou art <hi>aſcended up, far above all Heavens.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="sermon">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:59072:60"/>
            <head>SIXTH SERMON ON <hi>Whit-Sunday,</hi> OR <hi>The Ineſtimable Gift, The Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>8. Acts 20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But Peter ſaid untohim, Thy Money periſh with thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt thought that the gift of God may be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with Money.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THis day of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> the <hi>Fifti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> or <hi>Jubilee</hi> from the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> hath in it two direct acts of a joyful <hi>Jubilee,</hi> 1. The <hi>Releaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of Priſoners; 2. The <hi>Reſtitution</hi> of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59072:61"/>Eſtates <hi>gratìs.</hi> Both theſe are effects of Chriſts <hi>Aſcenſion,</hi> (which we have late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treated) 4. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 8. <hi>When he aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up on high, he led Captivity captive, and gave gifts unto men.</hi> In the former, The <hi>Releaſing,</hi> we are freed from that bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, whereunto ſin had brought us.</p>
            <p>In the Latter, our <hi>Reſtitution,</hi> we take again our firſt Happineſs, (loſt at the Fall) recovered, by the <hi>renewing</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt, 3. <hi>Tit.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>This is that <hi>Ineſtimable gift</hi> of God at this time ſent, which we moſt infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely undervalue, whilſt we think to value it at any temporal rate whatever; For this, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> offers that, (which <hi>Solomon,</hi> 10 Eccleſ. 19. ſaith) <hi>anſwers all things,</hi> Money: But <hi>Peter ſaid unto him, Thy Money periſh with thee, becauſe thou haſt thought that the gift of God may be purchaſed with money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Text is an <hi>Execration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In the Text,</hi> 4 <hi>parts.</hi>
               </note> wherin you have,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Perſon <hi>Execrating, Peter. Peter ſaid,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Perſon Execrated <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> v. 20. <hi>Peter ſaith unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:59072:61"/>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Execration</hi> it ſelf. <hi>Thy money periſh with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Reaſon of this <hi>Execration, Becauſe thou haſt though that the gift of God may be purchaſed with money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Perſon Execrating, <hi>Peter,</hi> who might well take on him this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, having generally with the reſt of the Apoſtles, (20. <hi>Joh.</hi> 23) and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly by himſelf (16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the power of the Keyes, for bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and looſing, for <hi>Abſolving</hi> and <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crating.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which power in <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, not <hi>Perſonally,</hi> tyed only to them, (but they receiving it, as <hi>Miniſters, Prieſts,</hi> or <hi>Preachers</hi> (as witneſſes their preceeding <hi>Miſſion,</hi> 20. <hi>Joh.</hi> 21. and <hi>Inſpiration</hi> peculiar to this Office, <hi>v.</hi> 22) was to be derived from them, to all who ſhould lawfully ſucceed in the ſame function. <hi>See</hi> Bp. Andr. <hi>of the power of Abſol.</hi> p. 57.</p>
            <p>Wherefore at our entring into Holy Orders, together with Preaching the Word, we receive this <hi>Commiſſion;</hi> The Form is, <hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> whoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59072:62"/>ſins ye remit, they are remitted unto them, and whoſoever ſins ye retain, they are retained, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not but that Gods power is Ablo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, his Grace free, and unbounded, He can ſave without meanes, or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, but ordinarily, in the remitting, or retaining of ſins) he hath been pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to appoint, That the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper-houſe,</hi> Heaven, ſhould concurre with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the <hi>Lower-houſe,</hi> the Paſtors of his Church on Earth, 18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, whatſoever ye ſhall bind on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven, and whatſoever ye ſhall looſe on earth, ſhall be looſed in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt having conferred this Honour on Eccleſiaſtical perſons, let men be very cautious how they <hi>deſerve,</hi> and they, how they <hi>pronounce</hi> their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Perſon <hi>Execrated, Simon Magus,</hi> a notable Sorcerer, <hi>v.</hi> 9. It is reported that in <hi>Claudius Caeſar's</hi> time there was a Statue ſet upon in <hi>Rome</hi> in Honour of him with this blaſphemous inſcription, <hi>Simoni Deo ſancto, Juſtin
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59072:62"/>Mart. Apol.</hi> 2. of his blaſphemies write <hi>Euſeb. Iren. Epiph.</hi> Of his ſtrange things he did, relates <hi>Egeſip. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. and <hi>Nicephor. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 22.27. He was Deified of the people, <hi>v.</hi> 10. afterwards a ſpecious Profeſſour, Baptized, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Apoſtles ſignes and wonders, <hi>v.</hi> 13. yet <hi>is not his heart right with God,</hi> v. 21. He embraceth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith, but for ſome baſe end, maketh Religion only a bait to fiſh for ſome Secular applauſe, and advantage. <hi>When Simon ſaw that through laying on of the Apoſtles hands the Holy Ghoſt was given,</hi> v. 18. <hi>for this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> v. 19. (not queſtioning but to make his Market of it again) <hi>He offered them money:</hi> But <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid unto him, <hi>Thy money periſh with thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Execration</hi> it ſelf, <hi>Thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney periſh with thee,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Thy Money go into diſtruction with thee or perdition, ſo <hi>Judas</hi> is called, 17. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The ſon of Perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and Gods final Judgment on the wicked is ſtyled (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 3.7.) <hi>The Perdition of ungodly men.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:59072:63"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Apoſtatizing ſo dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably as he did from the purity of the Faith he had profeſſed, and was bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into, <hi>v.</hi> 13. (which his blaſphemous, and vile proffers, did too openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate) is by the great Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi> (who as before hath been ſaid, had received the power of <hi>Binding,</hi> 16 <hi>Mat.</hi> 18) condemned as one Excommunicate from the Fellowſhip of the Spirit, <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>Thou haſt neither part nor lot in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and Retained in ſin, <hi>v.</hi> 23. <hi>Thou art in the gall of bitterneſs, and in the bond of iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy money periſh with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Phraſe will bear a twofold Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Leſſer,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Greater.</p>
            <p>The Firſt, Is a <hi>Delivering to Satan,</hi> for the caſtigation, or deſtruction of the fleſh, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. in order to the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Soul. Here, the party Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated was ſubject (by the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of ſome evil ſpirit, or otherwiſe) to divers tortures of Body, ſometimes to death it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:59072:63"/>
            <p>The Latter, or greater, is An <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema Maranatha,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. the heavieſt Curſe, the Fearfulleſt degree of Excommunication, under which who lay, could never here be reconciled to to the Church, but carryes this dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sentence with him, <hi>till the Lord ſhall come,</hi> to the laſt Judgment.</p>
            <p>Both theſe intimate Gods wrath on notorious Sinners, which when inflicted, <hi>Riches periſh,</hi> fail, ſtand us in no ſtead at all. 11 <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. 7 <hi>Ezec.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy money periſh with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God inflict on thee ſome temporal puniſhment, thy Purſe ſhall not be able to help, which they ſay come to paſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, by the breaking of his limbs on his pretended flight to heaven, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by diſcovering his fallacious Art, and ſo dying. See <hi>Egiſippus lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de excidio Hieroſolimitano, cap</hi> 2, <hi>Torauebatur Magus Aroſtoli gratia</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Decidat Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, ſic tamen ut nihil ſe potuiſſe vivens recognoſcat, &amp; ſtatim in voce</hi> Petri, <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicatis remigiis alarum quas ſumpſerat, corruit nec exanimatus eſt, ſed fracto debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liato<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> crure Aritiam conceſſit at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, ibi mortuus eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:59072:64"/>
            <p>This is a temporal Periſhing 22. <hi>Joſ.</hi> 20, 119 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.</p>
            <p>Or <hi>Thy Money periſh with thee</hi> (without repentance) be thou doomed to eternal damnation, this is called <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing</hi> too, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18.</p>
            <p>In this Firſt <hi>periſhing,</hi> (thy bodily pain) <hi>pereat Argentum,</hi> let thy Money be at a loſſe; (as indeed it ſhall) not able to relieve thee; Much leſs, if by obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and impenitential perſevering in ſin, thou ſhalt incurr the <hi>latter periſhing;</hi> perfect and perpetual Torment, both of ſoul and body, at the great and terrible day of the Lord, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. Then, <hi>pereat Argentum,</hi> Money ſhall run to nothing, at the general Conflagration, for as the old world by <hi>Water</hi> periſhed, <hi>v.</hi> 6. ſo muſt this by <hi>Fire, v.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Reaſon of the Execration; <hi>Becauſe thou haſt thought that the gift of God may be purchaſed with money.</hi> Here we are to Conſider Two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Holy Ghoſt is the Ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable gift of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What a <hi>Horrid ſin</hi> it muſt needs
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59072:64"/>be to think it may <hi>purchaſed with money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt is Gods Ineſtimable gift.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis 2 <hi>Gift</hi> of his, 14 <hi>Joh.</hi> 16, 17. 11 <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. Infinitely beyond all me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſo 'tis well; It is a <hi>Gift,</hi> we muſt have gon without it elſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis Gods <hi>ſpecial Gift</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The Gift of God, The Gift of all Gifts, not <hi>Datum,</hi> (as Bp. <hi>Andr.</hi> diſtinguiſheth in <hi>ſerm.</hi> 14. on <hi>Whitſun.</hi> pag. 748.) any worldly good thing, but <hi>Donum bonum &amp; perfectum, That good and perfect gift, that</hi> (this day) <hi>came down from above, from the Father of lights</hi> 1 <hi>James</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Gift</hi> are contained all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies of <hi>nature,</hi> and <hi>grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of <hi>Nature,</hi> ſuch as Reaſon, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Underſtanding, Arts, Policy, Government, Stength, Courage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Of <hi>Grace,</hi> ſuch as Faith, Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Temperance, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Every Feather of this <hi>Dove,</hi> 3 <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. is of Gold; Every drop of this <hi>Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> (this <hi>Water</hi>) precious, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.27.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59072:65"/>7 <hi>Joh.</hi> 38. Every ſpark of this <hi>Fire,</hi> beautiful, 2 <hi>Acts</hi> 3. Every gale of this <hi>Wind</hi> perfumed, <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>O ſi donum De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcires,</hi> (ſaith our Saviour, 4 <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.) <hi>if we knew but this Gift,</hi> (which cannot be but by <hi>receiving it,</hi> 2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.) how ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d we prize it!</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Gift,</hi> God formerly gave <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, verſe</hi> 11. The <hi>Gift</hi> of <hi>Healing, Miracles,</hi> &amp;c. And in this <hi>Gift,</hi> God ſtill gives us <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> for theſe we keep this <hi>Holy-day</hi> (ſaith Bp. <hi>Andrewes</hi>) and ſo ought to have for them, more then a <hi>Working-day</hi> accompt.</p>
            <p>Again, The Gifts which proceed from this Gift, ſuch as <hi>Preaching, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring</hi> the Bleſſed <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> &amp;c. are as good as no Gifts, but for this Gift to the Holy Ghoſt. The <hi>Word,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. is but a <hi>dead Letter,</hi> except the Spirit <hi>quicken</hi> it. There can be no Regeneration, or New birth, at Baptiſm, except (as in the Firſt Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 1 <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.) <hi>the Spirit move upon the Water.</hi> In the Lords Supper, the <hi>Fleſh</hi> 6 <hi>Joh.</hi> 63. profiteth nothing, if the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:59072:65"/>be away; nor can we <hi>Pray</hi> as we ought, except the Spirit <hi>help</hi> us, 8 <hi>Rom.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p>The Gift of God, <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> (through Jeſus Chriſt) is Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us by the Gift of the Spirit: for though Chriſt on his part, hath finiſhed the work of our Redemption, 19 <hi>Joh.</hi> 30. by ſetting his hand to it, (his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings on the Croſs,) yet this <hi>deed,</hi> is not forcible to us without the <hi>ſeal,</hi> 4 <hi>Eph.</hi> 30. and <hi>witneſs</hi> of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> 8 <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Giſt,</hi> God giveth <hi>peace</hi> to the <hi>diſſenting,</hi> 4 <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. <hi>inſtruction</hi> to the <hi>ignorant,</hi> 14 <hi>Joh.</hi> 26. <hi>guidance</hi> to the <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious,</hi> 16 <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. <hi>comfort</hi> to the <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate, verſe</hi> 6, 7. <hi>memory</hi> to the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getful,</hi> 14 <hi>Joh.</hi> 26. To ſpeak all at once, in this <hi>Gift</hi> God giveth us rich diſcoveries of himſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. nay <hi>Himſelf</hi> withal, hereby the Almighty <hi>dwells among us,</hi> 68 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. <hi>ſee</hi> Bp. Hall <hi>'s Paraph, on the place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Holy Ghoſt now being ſo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely Ineſtimable a <hi>Gift</hi> of God, (as you have heard) what <hi>a horrid ſin</hi> muſt it
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:59072:66"/>needs be, to think, it may be <hi>purchaſed with money?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What <hi>Ingratitude</hi> is this to the <hi>Giver,</hi> what <hi>Indignity</hi> and <hi>affront</hi> offered to the <hi>Gift</hi> it ſelf?</p>
            <p>A <hi>Gift</hi> (be it what it will) as a Gift, 'tis abſurd to value it, much more to put a temporal and corruptible price upon an incorruptible and Eternal purchaſe: a thought of this cannot be endured: <hi>Thy money periſh with thee, becauſe thou haſt thought that the Gift of God may be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with money.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>Application.</head>
               <p>Is the holy ghoſt ſo ineſtimable a gift not to be thought on, with a money purchaſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This condemnes <hi>Romes market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it,</hi> by ſelling <hi>Crowns, Miters, Braiers, Pardons &amp;c.</hi> as <hi>Mantuan</hi> teſtifies.</p>
               <q>—Venalia nobis Templa, Sacerdotes, altaria ſacra, Coronae, Ignis, Thura, Preces, Caelum eſt venale Deuique.</q>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:59072:66"/>
               <p>What doth the Apoſtle here, (whom they ſo boaſt of as their prime Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan) refuſe <hi>Simons</hi> money, and will he now have <hi>Peter-pence?</hi> The Pope only hath coyned theſe exactions for himſelf, he deſires them not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Gift is ſuch in relation to the Receivers, have we then received this Ineſtimable gift? which we may know thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>By Sanctity of life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Holy Ghoſt, the third perſon in the Trinity, is peculiarly termed Holy, for that beſides the holineſs of <hi>Nature,</hi> (in which reſpect the Father and the Son are alſo holy) his <hi>Office</hi> is, to <hi>Sanctify</hi> the Church of God, to whom it agreeth in a ſpeciall manner; for where the Father Sanctifieth by the Son, and by the Holy Ghoſt, the Son from the Father and by the Holy Ghoſt; the Holy Ghoſt Sanctifieth from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and from the Son, by himſelf im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately.</p>
               <p>Where this 1. Spirit of holyneſs is
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59072:67"/>breathed into any man it creates in him a life of holyneſs, (and as the natural Spirit doth) at the <hi>heart</hi> it will <hi>beat,</hi> at the <hi>mouth</hi> it will <hi>breath,</hi> at the <hi>pulſe</hi> it will be <hi>felt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>heart</hi> it will cauſe new thoughts, new deſires, <hi>ſanè novum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perveniſſe ſpiritum, nova deſideria de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtram,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Bernard.</hi> In the <hi>mouth,</hi> new talke new communication, in the <hi>hands</hi> works of new obedience.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the effects of that <hi>new</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, (the holy Ghoſt) God promiſed to give 36. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>This Spirit when it makes a <hi>new creature,</hi> it begins at the <hi>heart,</hi> as the heart (they ſay) in any Animal, is <hi>primum vivens &amp; ultimum moriens</hi> lives firſt and dies laſt.) It Sanctifies the heart from all inward defilements, 15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. the Lips from evil ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 4. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 31. the Hands from any unlawful actions, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. Thus (if ſincerely ſurveying our <hi>thoughts, words,</hi> and <hi>works,</hi> we find them <hi>holy,</hi>) we may thence inferr, <hi>We have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:59072:67"/>
               <p>And as by <hi>Sanctity of life</hi> we may judge of the receiving this Ineſtimable Gift, (for this <hi>Dov,</hi> will not light on <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion,</hi> This <hi>Water</hi> will <hi>cleanſe,</hi> this <hi>fire</hi> will <hi>refine,</hi> this <hi>wind</hi> will <hi>fan</hi> thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a <hi>clean</hi> box it muſt be, that is to hold this <hi>Ointment.</hi>)</p>
               <p n="2">2. By <hi>Humility.</hi> 57 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 15. This Dove implies meekneſs, this water forſakes the Hills, to viſit the low Valleys; the leſs we think of our ſelves, the higher eſteem God hath of us, <hi>(a meek and quiet ſpirit is with him of great Price)</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. c. 4. to whom he ſends this rich preſent, the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 4 <hi>James</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By <hi>Boldineſs in ſuffering for Chriſt,</hi> this we ſee in the Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> 4 <hi>Acts</hi> 8.13. and the reſt, 5 <hi>c.</hi> 40, 41, 42. and <hi>Stephen</hi> 7 <hi>c.</hi> 54, 55. Yet let men beware here, the Spirit of contradiction, obſtinate gain ſaying of Magiſtrates, and <hi>ſpeaking evil</hi> of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, (correcting Delinquency) be not miſtaken for the Spirits <hi>Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity</hi> in perſecution.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:59072:68"/>
               <p n="4">4. By <hi>charity,</hi> 4 <hi>James</hi> 5. Do you think that the Spirit of God (ſaith the Apoſtle) which we profeſs to have dwelling in us <hi>luſteth to envy?</hi> (ſo Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Hall</hi> in his Paraph. on the place) This <hi>fire</hi> from Heaven, 2 <hi>Acts</hi> 3. is to melt us into pity, not like that men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, 9 <hi>Luke</hi> 54. to deſtroy preſently all who diſlike us: who ſavoureth of the <hi>gall</hi> of bitterneſs, v. 23. <hi>hath no part nor lot</hi> in this Gift.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Where this Gift is received, the love of God hereby ſo ſhed abroad in the heart, 5 <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. will neceſſarily run out at the mouth in all joyful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of <hi>gratitude,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thanks be unto God for his unſpeakable Gift,</hi> 2 Cor. 9. c. 15. This effect it wrought on the Gentiles on whom it was poured out, 10 <hi>Acts</hi> 46. they preſently found new Tongues to <hi>magnifie</hi> God.</p>
               <p>They that <hi>have taken</hi> this Gift, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be <hi>taken with</hi> it, (and for the Gift ſake) with the <hi>day,</hi> it deſcended on: Therefore let us keep the Feaſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. c. 8.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:59072:68"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Let us labour after this ineſtimable Gift.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. By <hi>Prayer.</hi> 'Tis called the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of <hi>Supplication,</hi> 12 <hi>Zech.</hi> 10. not only becauſe it helps our infirmities <hi>in</hi> Prayer, 8 <hi>Rom.</hi> 26. but alſo <hi>by</hi> it, it is attained; we draw in this Holy Breath, 20 <hi>Joh.</hi> 22. by opening our mouths in Petitioning to God for it, 11 <hi>Luke</hi> 13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By <hi>Hearing.</hi> Thus St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Auditory, 2 <hi>Acts</hi> 1. and <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Family received it. <hi>Acts</hi> 10. c. 44. As, <hi>(in naturalibus)</hi> in things natural (faith Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi>) the Breath and the voice, go together; ſo the Spirit and the Word in the practice of Religion. The Lord was found moſt chiefly in the <hi>Voice,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19. c. 12. His Spirit is an Inſtructive Word, 30 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 21. and deſcends (as on this day) in <hi>Tongues,</hi> 2 <hi>Acts</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By the <hi>Sacraments.</hi> The Spirit
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59072:69"/>of God moveth upon the Water in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and neceſſarily accompanieth the Body and Blood of Chriſt, in the Lords <hi>Supper,</hi> 2 Act. 38. <hi>Repent and be</hi> baptized, <hi>and ye ſhall receive the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> So is this Gift given us, by Chriſts giving us himſelf to eat, 6 <hi>Jo.</hi> 57. <hi>He that eateth me, he ſhall live by me;</hi> now, if the <hi>breath</hi> and the <hi>ſpirit</hi> be all one, 20 <hi>Joh.</hi> 22. ſo is the <hi>breath</hi> and <hi>life,</hi> 2 <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. and the <hi>ſpirit</hi> and the <hi>life,</hi> 6 <hi>Joh.</hi> 63. They then that can make Chriſt a <hi>Body</hi> in the Euchariſt, muſt make him his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit too, ſince they cannot be ſevered, (for (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi>) The fleſh that was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, this is never without the Holy Ghoſt by whom it was conceived) and ſo they can do more for <hi>him,</hi> than they can for <hi>themſelves;</hi> for who can give himſelf life, or Being? No, the Body and Blood of Chriſt, (whereby we receive his Spirit) are verily and indeed (ſaith our Church-Catechiſm) taken of the faithful, (ſpiritually, not by <hi>ſence,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. c. 16.) in the Lords Supper.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59072:69"/>Thus is our Soul refreſhed by his <hi>fleſh,</hi> in the <hi>bread,</hi> and his <hi>blood,</hi> in the <hi>wine;</hi> and ever with this <hi>blood</hi> there runneth an Artery with plenty of <hi>Spirit</hi> in it: This <hi>cup,</hi> is a cup of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. c. 13. as may eaſily be perceived by that ſtrange enlivening wrought in us after the drinking it; then how lyes the Soul proſtrate with joy, at the feet of her dear Saviour, raviſhed with the ſence of her pardon, and the aſſurance of Gods love? now ſhe hath received a freſh life of devotion, whereby ſhe caſts off her old corruptions, reſolves upon new obedience, and is tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>thankfulneſs.</hi> Theſe are the effects of Gods ineſtimable Gift, (the Spirit) received in the Sacrament: which though it cannot be found in the <hi>Veins</hi> of the richeſt <hi>Mines</hi> (not to be <hi>purchaſed with Money</hi>) yet here it is to be found in the <hi>ſtreams</hi> of Chriſts <hi>blood,</hi> and that we may ſo find it, <hi>God of his infinite mercy grant,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
